<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A mirour for magestrates of cyties Representing the ordinaunces, policies, and diligence, of the noble emperour, Alexander (surnamed) Seuerus, to suppresse and chastise the notorious vices noorished in Rome, by the superfluous nomber of dicing-houses, tauarns, and common stewes: suffred and cheerished, by his beastlye predecessour, Helyogabalus, vvith  sundrie graue orations: by the said noble emperor, co[n]cerning reformation. And hereunto, is added, A touchstone for the time: containyng: many perillous mischiefes, bred in the bowels of the citie of London: by the infection of some of thease sanctuaries of iniquitie. By George Whetstones. Gent.</title>
            <author>Whetstone, George, 1544?-1587?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15039</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119730</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854937</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854937</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20399</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15039)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20399)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1047:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A mirour for magestrates of cyties Representing the ordinaunces, policies, and diligence, of the noble emperour, Alexander (surnamed) Seuerus, to suppresse and chastise the notorious vices noorished in Rome, by the superfluous nomber of dicing-houses, tauarns, and common stewes: suffred and cheerished, by his beastlye predecessour, Helyogabalus, vvith  sundrie graue orations: by the said noble emperor, co[n]cerning reformation. And hereunto, is added, A touchstone for the time: containyng: many perillous mischiefes, bred in the bowels of the citie of London: by the infection of some of thease sanctuaries of iniquitie. By George Whetstones. Gent.</title>
                  <author>Whetstone, George, 1544?-1587?</author>
                  <author>Severus Alexander, Emperor of Rome, 208-235.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 36 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richarde Iones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At foot of title: Authorised and allowed.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A.i.".</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A mirour for maiestrates of cities.</note>
                  <note>"An addition: or touchstone for the time" has separate title page; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Social problems --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Social problems --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20399:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20399:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A MIROVR For Mageſtrates OF CYTIES. <hi>Repreſenting the Ordinaunces, Policies,</hi> and Diligence, of the Noble Emperour, ALEXAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER (ſurnamed) SEVERVS, to ſuppreſſe and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe the notorious Vices nooriſhed in Rome, by the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous nomber of Dicing-houſes, Tauarns, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Stewes: Suffred and cheeriſhed, by his beaſtlye Predeceſſour, HELYOGABALVS, vvith ſundrie graue Orations: <hi>by the ſaid noble Emperor, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning Reformation.</hi> AND HEREVNTO, IS ADDED. A Touchſtone for the Time: <hi>Containyng: many perillous Miſchiefes, bred</hi> in the Bowels of the Citie of LONDON: <hi>By the Infection of ſome of theaſe</hi> Sanctuaries of Iniquitie.</p>
                  <p>By GEORGE WHETSTONES. Gent.</p>
                  <p>✿ VIRTVTE, NON VI.</p>
                  <p>¶<hi>Printed at</hi> London, <hi>by</hi> Richarde Iones 1584</p>
                  <p>¶Author <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d and allowed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20399:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20399:2"/>
                  <head>To the Right Honorable, <hi>Sir</hi> Edward Osburne, <hi>Knight, Lord</hi> MAIOR, of the famous Cittie of LONDON: <hi>To the Right Worſhipfull, his Aſſiſtantes, the</hi> Aldermen: And to their learned Counſeller, <hi>M. Seriant</hi> Fleetwood, <hi>Recorder of the</hi> ſame CITIE: his approoued good Frende and Kinſman.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, and worthie Maieſtrates: Among the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ther is a by Prouerb, ORPHEVS <hi>can deſcribe</hi> Hell, <hi>better then</hi> ARI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STOTLE: raiſed vpon a Fable, that he fetched his Wife from thence: which is none other, then a confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, of the ſound Reaſon of PLAVTVS: That, <hi>Of more validitie, is the ſight of one eye, then the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of ten eares: for, in that a man ſeeth, is Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and in that he heareth, may be Error.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Right Honorable, and Reuerent, I vſe this EXOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIVM, to take away the Contempt, which, the plain Diſcouerie of my MIROVR may breede, that make ſo ſharp a Declaration of Vices, as if they raigned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chaſtiſement? And do I, with the Deformytie of Rome, reformed, by Addition, entreate of Abuſes? or more, of daingerous Miſchiefes, incloaſed in the Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elles of this famous Cittie? I doo: and do acknowledg withall, that you are Iudges of offenders, within your limittes, and with the Scourdge of Lawe, you chaſten them, or with the Swoorde of Iuſtice, do cutte them ſhort, as you finde them: as you finde them, I ſaye: E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al-be-it,
<pb facs="tcp:20399:3"/> by the teſtimonie of Holy writ, both you, and all principal Mageſtrates, haue on Earth, the names and places of Goddes: yet with your fauours, in your, and their Iudgementes, are (often) ſhowen the Infyrmyties of men: your ſightes are not inviſible, and (therfore) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, that you haue viſible Lightes, in obſcure Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. A Phyſition, can not ſee euery ſecrete griefe, but vpon Reuealement, may applie a curable Medicine for a hidden Diſceaſe: Euen-ſo, many can diſcouer the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, the Mageſtrate ſeeth not: but the Mageſtrate (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, muſt remedie the ſame. And where (ſay you) haue I knowledge, of theſe concealed Abuſes? Forſoothe, <hi>In Hell: where al ſinne and Iniquitie, is as appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, as Godlineſſe &amp; Vertue is in Heauen, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mee ſeemeth, I here you anſwer: That ſmale is the Maruaile, if you come not there, to harken after Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: when the ſayng is: <q>In Hel there is no Redemption.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>In very trueth: If Cuſtom haue not made you bold, ye could no ſooner enter into the <hi>Common Dicinge Houſes, or Hell, in, and about</hi> London: (So, I maye name them, by the Aucthoritie of CORNELIVS AGRIPPA, who ſaith: that, <hi>the Art was, firſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed by the Deuil:</hi>) But, you wold imagin the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye, dampned, and you, your ſelues in daunger, to bee preſently deſtroyed: Gods vengeance is ſo greuouſlye tempted: For, the Deuill can breathe out Iniquitie, no faſter, then his Angelles, there aſſembled, outrage God with the horribleſt blaſphemies that may be imagined, and too damnable to be reported: What followeth there, wher this deſpight is done vnto the eternal God? Mary, no villanie, may be vnthought, nor vnwrough to preiudice men.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20399:3"/>
                  <p>It is euery mannes Caſe, that hath care of his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytie, to be Suters for Reformation: the euill, is of the Nature of the Oyle of Ieat, that conſumeth the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, &amp; periſheth not the Bone. The Marow &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of this happy Realme, I mean the Abilitie of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, is much weakned and, almoſt waſted, by haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of theſe vngratious Houſes: Yet, for that the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes be not reprooued, the Remedies ar not applied:</p>
                  <p>Not ſo fewe, as three hundred Gentlemen, of liuing, are at this Day, more then halfe vndone, by the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous frequenting of Dicing-houſes: how many, here tofore, haue ben cleane ſuncke, would mooue pittie to nomber: And for the welfare of ſuch as ſhall followe, it is highe time, the Corruption were purged: And as the nombers of Gentlemen, by this meanes decayed, are great: ſo, the nombers of thoſe that liue like Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vpon their ſpoyles, are greater: For, if the Shifters in &amp; within the leuel of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don, were, truely, muſtered, I dare boldly ſay, they would amaze a Pettie Armye, I pray god, an eaſie incourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, arme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to a ciuil Miſchiefe: for if their forfeats were wel knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I fere, thei do acts as ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trus: but my meaning is, not to ſuſpect or acuſe any in particuler, although, ther be mani, <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                     </hi> too boldly offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. I wiſh <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                     </hi> their Couerts wer diſcouered, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſtice wold ſoon find their faults, or repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſhew their ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. My Diſcouerie, being by your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes read, the lothſomnes of this Miſchief can not but diſtemper your ſences: and for your ſafeties, the Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I truſt, ſhalbe ſpeedely purged: And in this comon benefite, this glorious Monument ſhall remain of your godly Trauayles.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>London, as ſhe is the Honor of her Countrey:</l>
                     <l>So, is ſhe become the liuely Example of vertue.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20399:4"/>
                  <p>If this Saiynge, bee written vppon her Gates, and <hi>A Whyp and a Halter the Signe of a Dicinghouſe:</hi> Vnthriftes and their Familiars, would, quickly, liue in other Corners, It is (almoſt) incredible, what beaſtly eſtate, HELIOGABALVS, left Rome: as great a wonder, how ſoone his good Succeſſor ALEXAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER, repayred her Ruines: A Briefe of bothe, whoſe Gouernments, I haue ſet down in the beginning of this Treatiſe, to ſhowe, how mightie ſinne will grow with a little lybertie: and how ſoone, it is quailed with ſeuere Correction.</p>
                  <p>We haue the Image of Vertue, too our Soueraigne Queene ELIZABETH: the Sages of ATHENS, to her moſt Honorable priuie Counſell: graue Iudges in iuditiall places, and worthie Maieſtrates, to examine Offences: by Gods and whoſe prouidence, our Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytie, is ſo famous, as all the worlde enuie and feare vs. How great a foile, weare it then, that we ſhuld deuoure one another, when, of our ſuperfluytie, many a hungry Nation is ſatisfied.</p>
                  <p>The prudent Maieſtrates, haue alredie looked into our laſciuious inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; haue enacted Medicineable Lawes, for theſe Infirmyties: But the ſeuereſt Lawes, are not other, then written threatninges, without Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, of whoſe vengeance, all men may heare and no man doth feele. In times paſt, a Proclamation, would keepe men in awe: and nowe, an Example of Iuſtice, ſcarſe, makes the wicked to chaunge countenaunce: but althouge, a Braynſicke Iade, wyll ronne with a Snaffle, a ſharpe Bitte wyll bridle him: though an Offender do ieſt to here a Penall Statute proclaymed, and ſay: tuſh, the effect of this, will be ſoone forgotten: yet, in the
<pb facs="tcp:20399:4"/> meanewile, ſcowrge him with the paine, and hee will crie, Peccaui.</p>
                  <p>To reforme the inconueniences Embleamed in this Myrrour, neede neither Machauils Pollycies, nor new Seſſions of Parliament: The Remedies are alredie eſtabliſhed, and Adminiſtration, will ſoone worke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment: Reformation belongeth to the Magiſtrate although, the benefite be generall: I (onely) of Zeale, diſcouer vnſufferable faultes, but deale not with faultie men, whom I referre to publique Iuſtice: And too your Cenſures I preſent my Trauayle, and at Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, my ſelfe: Vowinge, in Actions of a true Subiect, to ſeeke the Honour of this famous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: to ſhowe my ſelfe worthy of my deceaſed father, who liued longe in good Credit amonge you, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng dead, is regiſtred for a good man: no more, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of perfect deſires,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>To your Honour and Worships, George Whetſtones.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20399:5"/>
                  <head>To the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the yong Gentlemen, of the Innes of Court.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight VVorshipfull,</hi> and Worthie Gentlemen (of the <hi>Innes of Court:</hi>) vnto you, as vnto one of the faireſt Ornaments of this happy Realme, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende the benefite of this ſmall Treatiſe: And I am wel perſwaded, in this Dedication, that I ſalute the beſt parte of all the yong Gentlemen of <hi>Englande:</hi> For, what Courſe ſo-euer, they afterwardes ſollowe, there are very fewe Gentlemen, but, either are, or haue ben of your Societie: It is verie wel knowen, that theſe famous Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, are the firſt intertayners of your Lybertie.</p>
                  <p>For, (notwithſtandyng) in your Gouernments, there are many good and peaceable Orders, yet your chiefeſt Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, is by the Purſe. Thoſe that are diſpoſed, ſtuddie the Lawes: who ſo liketh, without checke, maye follow Dalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: And (certainly) the wanton Alectiues, which you (con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuallie) behold, are not vnlike the <hi>Sirenes</hi> Inchauntments (were Poets faynings true:) you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuallie walke by the Adamant Rockes, whiche drawe Siluer and Gold, as faſt as Iron and Stéele: you muſt be armed with more experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence then the capacytie of yong yeares: or els, aſſure your ſelues, that Repentance wyll vnloſe your Fetters: there is an olde Prouerb: <hi>Euil Companie, corrupteth good maners:</hi> And (truely) I cannot ſee, how yong men, of the beſt educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: ſhould eſcape vnpoyſoned, when vice is ſo conuerſant with Elder yeares.</p>
                  <p>O how happie were it for your Poſterytie, if, <hi>the Innes of the Court,</hi> were farre from <hi>Dieyng-houſes,</hi> or <hi>Dicing-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> with their Originall, the Deuill. But, if you can not be thus ſeperated, this little Booke, wyll (with regarde) guide you as ſafe, as the Clue of threede did <hi>Theſeus,</hi> in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berinth. Theſe Houſes (outwardly) are of the ſubſtance of other Buildinges, but within, are the Botches and Byles
<pb facs="tcp:20399:5"/> of Abhomynation: they are lyke vnto déepe Pittes, couered with ſmoothe Graſſe, of which, men muſt be warned, or els, they can hardly auoide that their eye can not diſcouer:</p>
                  <p>You can haue, nofairer warnings then the ſteppes of your Companions falles, nor I, a more fortunate Rewarde for my trauaile, then to ſee you (worthie Gentlemen) to flooriſh.</p>
                  <p>I beſeeche you, to be aduiſed: It is a more precious mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to ſhun a Miſchiefe, by other mennes harmes, then to learne the goodnes of a thing, by the loſſe therof. This ſharp Diſcouerie, will make your fléering Deceiuers, my open Enemies: but I ſhalbe well ſtrengthned, if my true Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, breede in you a diſdaine of their fellowſhyp, &amp; let them ſpurne their woorſte, they hurt them ſelues, that are angrie with good Admonition. I dedicate this Booke to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtrates. to whome, appertaineth the chaſtiſment of euyll liuers, your woorſt enemies: I dedicate to you (courteous Gentlemen) the Fruits of Noble <hi>Alexanders</hi> Counſelles, as beſeeming your worthineſſe: I am but his Trouch-man, and your truſtie frend. And (truely) your wiſdomes may make his graue Counſelles more profitable then their ſeuere Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline: for the Medicine is of more value, that preſerueth Health, then that which cureth Sickneſſe. The health of a Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is Honour &amp; actions of vertue: in which, <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> (liberally) inſtructeth you: The Maladie, nay, death of a Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is an vndoyng to the poſterytie, which is haſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, by the ſucking of Shifters: Of whome, I (conſtantly) hope, the good Maieſtrates will eaſe you: I leaue further Ceremonies, in my Preface, leaſte I ſeeme to iudge your Wiſdomes, who are (for Learninge) a faire Beautie of the Common-wealth: my plaine Methode, in writing, ſhoweth you a large hole to ſée Daye, which is ynouffe (with an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntage) who retayne the vertue, to drayne Honie from a Weede: I ende to trouble you, at this time: but in no time, will leaue to bée:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your aſſured Frende: <hi>George Whetſtones.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="encomium">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20399:6"/>
                  <head>Ad candidum Lectorem: IN LAVDEM OPERIS.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SI te cura iuvat ſanctarum (Candide) Legum,</l>
                     <l>Aut inculpatae praecepta ſalubria vitae:</l>
                     <l>Hinc Exempla petas, Morum ſit norma tuorum</l>
                     <l>Hic Liber, et SPECVLO te contempleris in iſto,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nam fugienda tibi quae ſint induſtrius Author</l>
                     <l>Quaeqae ſequenda docet. Liber et labor illius omnis</l>
                     <l>Huc ſpectant: Aleas vites, nec Teſſera curae,</l>
                     <l>Nec Gula, nec Luxus, nec deſidis Otia vitae</l>
                     <l>Sint tibi: ſed Mores compti, caſtiſſima vita,</l>
                     <l>Et Labor, et rebus virtus exercita duris</l>
                     <l>Quae Patriam iuſtis defen dere poſſit in Armis,</l>
                     <l>Haec Summa eſt Operis, noſtriqae hîc meta laboris.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>IOANNES BOTREVICVS.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>¶Faultes eſcaped, the Author being abſent.</head>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Leafe.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Side.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Lyne.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Fault.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Correction.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1.</cell>
                           <cell>1.</cell>
                           <cell>16.</cell>
                           <cell>no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth,</cell>
                           <cell>in no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>7.</cell>
                           <cell>1.</cell>
                           <cell>9.</cell>
                           <cell>an Abſurditie,</cell>
                           <cell>no Abſurditie.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>8.</cell>
                           <cell>2.</cell>
                           <cell>30</cell>
                           <cell>his own Daughter.</cell>
                           <cell>his owne Death.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>9.</cell>
                           <cell>1.</cell>
                           <cell>13.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gaius</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Caius.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>10.</cell>
                           <cell>1.</cell>
                           <cell>18.</cell>
                           <cell>Laborers</cell>
                           <cell>barbarous</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>15.</cell>
                           <cell>2.</cell>
                           <cell>19.</cell>
                           <cell>knights of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land.</cell>
                           <cell>knightes of the Band.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>21.</cell>
                           <cell>1.</cell>
                           <cell>2.</cell>
                           <cell>attempting</cell>
                           <cell>attempt.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>21.</cell>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>2.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>innoia.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>muoia</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>28.</cell>
                           <cell>1.</cell>
                           <cell>11.</cell>
                           <cell>forgetteth</cell>
                           <cell>geueth</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>26.</cell>
                           <cell>2.</cell>
                           <cell>22.</cell>
                           <cell>done</cell>
                           <cell>due</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell cols="5">In the next Line folowing, for reuerenced, reade, reſerued.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20399:6"/>
                  <head>A Mirrour for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtrates of Citties.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>FTER THAT THE GOOD</hi> Emperour <hi>Alexander</hi> (ſurnamed) <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerus,</hi> for his ſharp correcting of vice, had reſtored the authoritie of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and had giuen breathe vnto their good Lawes: of whom the one ſate without reuerence, and the other were read and not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, through the inordinate lyberties, and Priue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadges giuen vnto vice, by that vncleane Monſter <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> his Predeceſſor: Of the ſuddaine, <hi>Rome</hi> was brightned with the vertues of Iuſtice, as the world with the beames of the Sunne, after a horrible and darke tempeſt. But as there is no aſſurance of faire weather vntill the ſkie be cleare from clowdes, ſo (which well forſaw this good Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour) there can be no common wealth a grounded peace and proſperitie, where there are not Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers to fynde out offenders, as well as Iudges to chaſten offences: In ſo much, in the prime of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, accompanied with many graue Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, as this good Emperour went vnto the Senat, in his paſſage hee might ſee the Cittyzins buſielye
<pb facs="tcp:20399:7"/> exerciſed in their ſeuerall trades: he incountred the Gentlemen in ciuil attire, and of euerie eſtate, found both himſelfe and his Senators, ſaluted with much honour, reuerence and dutie.</p>
                  <p>And being in the Senate houſe, mounted in the iudiciall Throne, he ſate long, and was litle occupy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with crimynall cauſes.</p>
                  <p>The Senators, no little gloried, that (appealing vnto the iudgement of <hi>Alexander</hi>) they might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully boaſt, that <hi>Rome,</hi> which was late a Forreſt of wilde beaſtes, or to ſpeake more properlie, a den of theeues, a Sanctuarie for Ruffens, a priueledge for Strumpets: a place in whiche no vice was forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, nor vertu co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, by their great wiſdomes was brought into ſo good an order, as <hi>Alexanders</hi> eyes could beholde no open offenders, nor his eares heare of any ſecreat offences. In-ſo-much, as after his returne to the Pallace, they lauded the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, with many acclamations of vertue, attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this happy reformation vnto his pietie, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, and Iuſtice: thinking, that in giuing of hym this ſoueraigntie, he would returne the praiſes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their paineful-trauels, with the incouragement, that the magnanimious <hi>Caeſar</hi> gaue vnto his ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, ſaying: that <hi>their bloods wrot honor in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, and therfore how precious he eſteemed his owne honor, ſo carefull he was of their welfare.</hi> But <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> although he were ſecond to none, in the regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and the rewarding of vertuous Maieſtrates, yet leaſt by thinking, that this outwarde reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, had in the common wealth ſetled an inwarde amendement, and thereby they ſhoulde growe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligent
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20399:7"/> in the adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of their waighty char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, he with a light regarde, attended his owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued praiſes, to reaue them of the hope of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar commendations: yea, that they might wel know that all that gliſtered was not Golde, that alwaies the inwarde harte, was not diſcouered by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward habit: he compared the beſt gouerned Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth vnto a faire Aple, which being ſerched, hath a Core, and that the worthy Senators, might perceaue their errours, and to amende what was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of their owne duties, and neceſſarie to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh a happye gouernment, in this graue and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Oration hee ſet downe the daungerous eſtate of the publique weale: and with-al, a perfect reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die for the feſtred and inwarde maladies.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="oration">
                              <head>The firſt Oration of Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander, the Emperour, to the Senators.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Moſt graue and reuerende Fathers, we not a litle reioyce, through the grace of the immortal Gods, and your great wiſdomes, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the famous Rome, but yeſterday (in compariſon) infamed with al abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, by the priueleges of our beaſtly predeceſſor, who meriteth neither the name of Emperour, nor man, nowe in poſſeſſion of her aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent vertues: And as we confeſſe, that by the deuine and heroyicall bleſſinges, the hoareſed voyce of Iuſtice is cleared: So wee like-wiſe hope, by the ſame graces, the remembraunce of vice and iniquitie ſhal-be rooted out.
<pb facs="tcp:20399:8"/> But good Senators, to diſcontinue a proſperous begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, with a ſlouthfull imagination, that the Common weale is ſounde, becauſe no infyrmities appeare, is the vnhappie meane, to blaſte the fruites, of your well im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed wiſdomes, and to inpreſſe an vncurable Canker in the bowels of Rome. The practiſers of Chirurgerie very well know, that an olde and deepe feſtred ſore, wil with eaſie working of the Surgion, outwardly ſeeme to heale, but if there bee not Corſiues applied, to eate out the roote thereof, this ouer haſtie healing will breake foorth vnto a more greeuous maladie. Good Senators, vnto you al, it is wel knowen, that the publique weale hath of long time bin infected, with the moſt horrible vices, that euer humanitie practiſed: yea, ſo foule and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleane, as ciuill creatures are forbod to recite them, by the ſauadge inclination of that Monſter HELIOGA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BALVS, yea ſo lothſome and fylthy were his abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, as the worſer ſort of people, (his fauoured ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes) ſo deteſted his deteſtable and vile lyfe, as they haſted his ouer-long proroged death. Now that the immortall Gods haue inueſted vs with the Imperiall Maieſtie, ſmall is the wonder, though there appeare a reformation in the good, when the verie Reprobate were glutted with wickedneſſe. But reuerend Fathers, this ſweete alteration is no warrant to the Magiſtrate, to be ſlouthfull in his function, leaſt in not ſuruayinge of the beſt, the beſt them-ſelues be corrupted, as Moaths conſume the fineſt garmentes, where they be ſeeldome worne, and leſſe ouer-lookte: And although in the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort, this inconuenience is to be feared, in the worſer, this miſchiefe is to be certenly expected: they wil vpon euerie temptation returne to their naughtines as a Dog
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20399:8"/> to his vomit, and therfore theſe daungerous infyrmities in a Common wealth, muſt be cured as the skilfull Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion doth a feſtred ſore. Their cauſes muſt bee ſearched and their nouriſhing humors purged, and then amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment followeth. The cauſe of this inordinate luſt, this exceſſiue drunkenneſſe, this outragious prodigalitye, &amp; to be ſhort, this hel of iniquity among the Romanes, is euill education: of long time there hath bin no man ready to inſtruct them in vertues, nor willing to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend their vices, the nouriſhment of theſe euils are the Tauerns, Dicing places, and brothell houſes, of whiche Rome hath great ſtore, &amp; they greater ſtore of gueſtes: ſo that to rid the publique weale of this dangerous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, is fyrſte and cheefelye to inſtruct the youth in good maners, and next to abate the number of theſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous howſes, or at the leaſt, daylie to ouer-ſee their dooings.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Thus in breefe, I haue declared ſome of the hydden euilles, harboured in the bowels of Rome, which to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme your owne eyes muſt be as ready to fynde them out, as your eares attentiue to heare euils reported: you muſt bee as well Informers of offenders, as Iudges of offences: for the deſire of Iuſtice is to roote out iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the office of Iuſtices to inquire after euil lyuers: And without al doubt, in this carefull proceedinge, in your viſitations, you ſhall ſee ſufficient example of ſin, to occupie your Iudiciall places with correction. This vigilant care, will eternize your good beginnings with glorie, will eſtabliſh proſperitye in the weale puplique, will comforte the good, and bridle the wicked: yf not through the loue of vertue, yet for the chaſtninge of vice. Thus, you ſee it concerneth the inrichinge of
<pb facs="tcp:20399:9"/> the common wealth, in the ſeruice where-of the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of death, ſhould vnto you deeme pleaſant: In par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulers, it concerneth the proſperitie of your Children, Kinsfolke and Allies, for whoſe benefit you are borne to trauell: alſo it concerneth your owne honor, which you ſhould holde more precious then lyfe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as your Soueraigne, we coniure you, and as fathers of the Common-wealth beſeeche you, that you wyll continue our good beginninge, with the execution of the Emperours directions: and ſo we end as we begun, the proſperitie of Rome, ſhal highly laude the gracious goodnes of the gods, &amp; the greatnes of your wyſdoms.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>WHen the good Emperour, had in few words ended this waightie Oration, (or more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly graue admonition) the fatherly Senators ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring the ſound iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Alex.</hi> beinge of tender yeares &amp; vnexperienced, in pollices of gouernment, knew ſtraight-waies, that there was a negligence in their adminiſtration of Iuſtice, which his minde (continually exerciſed for the benefyt of the publique weale) forſaw, and to the profit therof, in this louing maner the ſame diſcouered.</p>
                  <p>To witneſſe that they throughly conceiued the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of his repoſed wordes, by their owne prudent deeds, they foorth-with wrought out the wholſome effects of his godly deſire: and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better to ſearch the core of vice &amp; iniquitie hid in the intrailes of <hi>Rome.</hi> Theſe good Maieſtrats vſed this pollicie, in diſguy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed habits they entred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Tauerns, common tables, victuling houſes, ſtewes &amp; brothel-harbors, without controleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, they viewed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> behauiors of the people, that thei might the better vnderſtand the ful of their abuſes: &amp; vpon diligent ſearche, what founde they?
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20399:9"/> forſooth, <hi>Rome</hi> like a painted ſtrumpet. The great boaſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they but lately made of her reformation, had no better aſſurance then this, a few of the good ſette forth their good diſpoſitions at large, &amp; many of the wicked, for a time helde in their lewde inclinations: but counterfetes wil vnto kinde, Coppex may holde print but not bide tutch with golde: euen ſo theſe hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrits, as place and opportunitie ſerued, bewraied their beaſtly natures. Among theſe franions, Coſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage was eſteemed lawful marchandiſe, &amp; dicinge, faire paſtime: lechery was held no ſin, nor chaſtity, vertu: ruffens were honored, &amp; the gods diſpiſed: the mouth of vertu was locked, &amp; vice ſpake through a trumpet. To be ſhort, among them was no law but diſorder, nor any thing publique but abhomination: neither poſſibli might it be otherwiſe: for by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> ruffens, bawdes &amp; ſuche other brothel birds, were made ſenators, yea, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baſeſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were maried to noble weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> could ſet abroche moſt villanies, bare the greateſt ſwayes: &amp; wher ſuch liberty is giuen to offend, ſin is ſo ſweete to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there wil appeere no difference betweene men &amp; beaſts, ſaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men do exceede beaſts in beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines: and in this accordeth deuine <hi>Plato,</hi> who ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe citties, in which ther are no ſeuere lawes to correct ſin, ar rather forreſts of monſters then places habitable for men, &amp; wher as ther was this corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in nature, there could be no alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hoped for but by diſcipline, which the ſequel well proueth.</p>
                  <p>The change of the gouernment, from a moſt vile vnto a moſt vertuous Emperour, purged ſimply, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, for although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exerciſe of naugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tineſſe, were not ſo ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as before, yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil diſpoſed
<pb facs="tcp:20399:10"/> knew where to ſtawle companions euen in the fore named Hell houſes, and which was moſt to bee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, among the ſcum of the Cittie, I meane Ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fians, Bawdes, Brokers, Cheters, Shifters and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: in theſe fylthie places, worthye Gentlemen and ſubſtantiall Cittezens were daylye founde, the one through vnthriftineſſe to waſt their patrimonie, the other by couetouſeneſſe to purchaſe the Deuill and all.</p>
                  <p>When the graue Senatours, had entred into the depth of theſe foule vlcers of the Publique weale, they founde that Dice, Drunkenneſſe and Harlots, had conſumed the wealth of a great number of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Gentlemen, whoſe Purſes were in the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of vile perſons, and their Landes at morgage with the Marchants, and how both the one and the other, were confederate to ſpoyle theſe Gallantes. They truly certifyed the Emperour, the dangerous eſtate of the Common wealth, how that by the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of theſe houſes, the Gentlemen had made this exchaunge with vile perſons: they were atty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the Gentlemens brauerie, and the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men diſgraced with their beaſtly maners: And ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much the caſe was the more to be pitied, for that the remedie was to be doubted: for al-be-it their infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons grew by the fylthie conuerſation with ruffens, Bawdes, and ſuche braue baggages, whiche was harde to be cured, that which ſhould comforte them in well dooinge, I meane their Landes, were in the poſſeſſion of the Marchantes, who of the gaine of their bargen will wage freendes to countenaunce their deceitfull dealinges, and then let them barke
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20399:10"/> their worſt, their aduerſaries will byte them with their owne teeth. Thus, poore Gentlemen, they are ſure to impaire their liuinges: how-be-it (perhaps) they amend theyr liues.</p>
                  <p>When the good Emperour, had attentiuely herd this (lamentable) report, hee foorth-with made this ſhort anſwer.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Graue Fathers, you haue certifyed vs no more, then by reaſon we ſenſibly foreſaw: it is therefore now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, that we by ſeueritie pluck vp the roots of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, which by ſufferaunce are growen to mightye bodies of ſin. Therfore our pleaſure is, that by expreſſe Commaundement, the Cittizins of Rome be-warned to appeare (to morrowe) be-fore vs, in the Theater of Rome, where they ſhall openly know their faultes: and by the graces of the immortall Gods, and counſell of our graue Senate, wee ſhall ſet downe remedies for this daungerous miſchiefe.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>This repoſed ſpeache of the Emperour, promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed good ſucceſſe to his graue determinations: in ſo muche, as the Senators ſettled in this hope, made (forthwith) Proclamation of the Emperours Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.</p>
                  <p>And at the appointed time, the grauer ſort of the Cittizins, with a multitude of the Communaltie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſembled, the Emperour and a choſen company of Senators, with a ſterne countenaunce paſſed by the people, and mounted in the Chayre of Maieſtie, as one diſtempered with a great paſſion, with an angrie Countenaunce and a ſtill tongue, hee ſetled his eyes vpon the Cittizins: And not-with-ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they ſaluted hym with many dutifull acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:
<pb facs="tcp:20399:11"/> as, <q>Liue long, O noble Emperour, the choſen of the Goddes, the Glory of the world, the Soueraigne of Kynges, and proſperytie of Roome:</q> yet he ſeemed neuer a whytte the more aſſable, as wyllynge they ſhould knowe that his wiſdome had ſearched their corrupt conſciences, &amp; (therfore) little regarded their dutiful gratulations: In the end, when the regarde of his diſpleaſed Countinaunce, had made them ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent with feare, or (rather) halfe dead with ſorrow, hee quickened them agayne, with this ſharpe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion: as followeth.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="oration">
                              <head>
                                 <hi>Alexanders Oration, to</hi> the Cittizyns of Roome.</head>
                              <p>IF we knewe, by what proper name to call you; by that name we would wyll you to giue attention, to the words we purpoſe to declare: If we ſhuld greet you with the reuerence due vnto Prieſtes, wee ſhould highly offende the Goddes and delude men: for, in you there is no Relygion to ſerue the Gods, nor Charytie to lyue Neighbourly among men. If we ſhuld ſalute you, as Senators, your own conſciences wold witneſſe that we mocked you: for the good Senators, trauell for the benefite of the Publique-weale, and you (only) la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for priuate lucre. It were ridiculous to call you Gentlemen: for they, by their magnanimous Vertues, inlarge the boundes of the Empyre, and you, thoughe you haue craft to diſpoſſeſſe Gentlemen of their lands, yet you lacke vallour to keepe the enemie from the ſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of your Cytties. VVhat? woulde you that wee ſhould call you, as the auncient Cittizyns were woont
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20399:11"/> to be called, good people of Roome? Beleeue me, this is no proper Title for you: for they and you differ in conditions, as good doth from bad. Thoſe Cittizyns or good people of Roome, by their Vertues, crowned Roome with the Honour of a Cittie, and more, with this Title: <hi>The Head of the Worlde:</hi> For, as diuine PLATO ſaith: <hi>it is not ſumptuous Buildynges, that giueth name of a Cittie, but the Ciuilytie and worthineſſe of the Cittyzyns:</hi> And on the contrary-parte, you pollute Roome with ſo many abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as where in times paſt, ſhe hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap> called the head of the world, ſhe may now be as aptly called: <hi>the tayle of iniquitie:</hi> If none of all theſe titles belong vnto you: what name ſhuld we then giue you? you be of Rome: lyue in Roome, and haue your ſuſtenance from Rome: all this hath Moathes in cloath, Canker-ruſt in Iron, &amp; Caterpillers in fruict: Then, <hi>you Moathes, Canker-ruſt and Caterpillers of Roome:</hi> giue eare vnto my words, which ſhowe you a more aſſured benefite then your own trauelles: The large Priuiledges of Abuſes, which you (of long tyme) haue inioyed, haue (by ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance made a cuſtom of ſin: &amp; therfore (in charytie (we are (firſt) bound, to admoniſh you with good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell: if that work no ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (of neceſſitie) we muſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten you with the Rod of Iuſtice: But, admit this lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie were without checke, you would be the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion of your own-ſelues: you haue experience of the Vermins to whome, wee (rightly) compared you: the Moathe, conſumeth the Cloath, and (in tyme) for lacke of ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, ſtarueth it ſelfe. The lyke doth the Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyller amonge Fruict, and with continuance, the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker-ruſt in Iron. And you, that deuoure the wealth of the CITTIE, dwell vppon the Poſſeſſions of
<pb facs="tcp:20399:12"/> the Gentlemen, and oppreſſe the multitude with bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage: what gayne you by this? By Crueltie, you pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe hatred of your Neighbours, and the Ambitious, wyll enuie your aboundance of wealth: and then, this followeth: If they can not be ſtrengthned with forein power, your familiars, wyll invade you with ciuil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention: For, among thoſe that haue liued prodigally, this rule is obſerued: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Purſes are emptie, their heads are occupied with a thouſand miſchiefes, to com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſſe a newe ſupply: And (which is moſt to be feared,) they be not ſo perrillous cunnyng in their practiſes, as they are Deuillyſh reſolute in their Executious: If they ſell you their landes, for money to ſpend riotouſly, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that help is paſt, they wyl cut off your heads, fyre your Houſes,<note place="margin">Pryde and want, cauſe of Sedition.</note> and ſacke this famous Cittie, to ſuſteine their laſciuious humoures: For (without ſpeciall grace) in prowd minds, want can not ſuppreſſe deſire to ſpend: You haue reade the experience in the Hiſtorie of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriftie CATTILINE and his Confederats, how he murdered the worthieſt Cittezins, without mercie, made ſpoyle of their Gooddes without lawe, and beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged Roome with a ſhrewde daunger: you are lyke to be partakers of their Afflictions, vnleſſe you bee more moderate in gayning of Gentlemens liuyngs, and they leſſe riotous in ſpendynge of your money. When PHILIP Kyng of MACEDONS, made warre vppon the PERSIANS, hauing intelligence, that they abounded in all maner of delicate vyandes, ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Garments and waſtful expences: he foorth with retyred his Army, and ſaid: it was needeleſſe too make warre vpon thoſe, that within a while, would cut one anothers throates. And truely, though PHILLIP
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20399:12"/> his anſwere were ſhort, his iudgement was waightie: for as mightie Ryuers wyll ſoone run drie, when their nooriſhyng Spryngs are turned another way: ſo weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Citties, can not, but be ſubuerted, when euery man doth cleane contrary to his function. Among the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, MAN is called, MICROCOSMOS, or a little worlde: for that in him is figured, a Modell of the glorie therof. If he reſemble the whole worlde, it were an abſurditie too make him a Figure of a wel-gouerned Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth: a man conſiſteth of diuers members, as head, body, Armes, legges. &amp;c. So doth a good Common-wealth, of diuers eſtates: as of a Kyng as Supreame-head and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der: of godly Prelates, as the heart and nooryſhers of deuine vertues: of graue Iudges, Maieſtrates and Counſellers, as the body and ſtrength of Common proſperytie: of worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as the Armes, hands and executioners of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtrates graue pollycies: of aduentrous Marchauntes, as the legges and trauaylers into forreigne countreyes, for their owne Countteyes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modytie: of Plowmen, and inferiour people, as the feete, which muſt run at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of euery other member. I ſay, where all theſe eſtates, dutifully, doo their Offices: where the Prince doth (iuſtly) commaunde: the Maieſtrates (adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly) direct: and inferiour Subiectes (faythfully) obey: there, where this Concorde is, peace and proſperytie, flooryſheth in their Citties, and feare, pineth the enuie of their borderyng enemies. On the contrary parte, where the head is crowned with a Pantofle, as the Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect of the vnconſtant multitude: where the paſſages of the heart, whiche is the Organe of the Soule, are fixed with the continuall exerciſe of ſinne, (the Figure that
<pb facs="tcp:20399:13"/> the Prelates ſownde Doctrine, are but wordes of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, and no cauſes of amendment: Where the breſt and bodie lyes naked to euery peryl, I meane, the good Maieſtrates, are neither reuerenced, feared, nor obayed: Where the handes are bownde to the knees, in token, that the Gentlemen are thrawle to the Marchantes:</p>
                              <p>Where, on the knees is faſtened a Cap and a feather, and about the legges, a Swoord and a Target buckled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in ſigne, that the Cittizyns deſire the honour they can not gouerne, and leaue their trauayles, whiche woulde inritch the Common-wealth: And where the feete, which ſhould trudge for euery neceſſary, ſhould be fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, in a payre of Stockes: as witneſſe of the poore La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borers bondage and oppreſſion, who, for their neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie trauelles, ought too bee cheeriſed. I ſay: as a man thus deformed, buckled and bownd on a heape, would ſoone peryſh, for want of ſuſtenance: euen-ſo, a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, thus confuſed, would ſoone be confown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for lacke of good Order. What Prince, that is Head and Soueraigne, of ſuch a ſauadge and brute peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? that wyll not (rather) wyſh, a Royall Tombe, then a Princely Pallace? for, in the one, he is priuyleaged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the outrage of enemies, &amp; in the other, he is not ſafe from the Treaſons of his own Subiects. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, you Vipers, which deſtroy one another, if our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng perſwaſions, may not alter your lewde diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: take the aduauntage of tyme &amp; my nakednes, giue me an vntimely death, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a diſhonorable raign: for (truely) I had rather die, while the walles of Roome doe ſtande, then liue to ſee her ſumptuous Buildynges on fite, whoſe ruine is at hand, vnleſſe, out of hand, you amend your corrupt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, &amp; the multitude, their naughtie maners.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:20399:13"/>
                  <p>AT theſe wordes, (with teares in their eyes) as Pleadges of ſorowful heartes: the people ſhou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted foorth with a lowde crye, their dutifull Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſaying.<q> O noble ALEXANDER, let the Torture of ten dearhes, be too eaſie a payne, for the man, whiche but ymagyneth thy Death: Lyue: and lyue long<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> O moſt noble Emperour, the lyfe of vs all, and the light of the Romaynes glorye.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>¶ Here Sorrow ſtopped their mouthes: but their diſmayed countenaunces, gaue full knowledge of their inwarde Repentance: ſo that the Emperour, both in wordes, lookes and geſture, (more mildely) continued his Oration: as followeth.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="oration">
                              <head>
                                 <hi>Continuance of Alexander</hi> his Oration, to the Cittizyns.</head>
                              <p>YOV wiſh him the vengeance of ten deaths, that ſhould; but imagine our death: And (certainly) Conſcience perſwadeth vs, your tonges do truely publyſh the conſents of your heartes: but ſmall is the difference, when death and deſolation is the ende, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you lay violent hands vpon vs, or murder vs with your horryble vices.<note place="margin">The ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe of a Kinge dome, endeth the raigne fo the Kinge.</note> The body that is in a Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, bringeth the head to the graue: euen-ſo, the ruine of the kingdom, endeth the raign of the king: he whoſe head groweth out of his ſhyn, whoſe eyes are ſet in his knees, whoſe feete are ioyned to his ſhoulders, &amp; his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther members (ſemblably) diſordred: wold you not (ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) take him for a Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter then a man? yea verely, and (doubtles) ſuch a creature wold peryſh by his deformy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ware he not by others foſtered for a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der: euen ſo, his prepoſterous ſhape in a Common-wealth, when
<pb facs="tcp:20399:14"/> euery eſtate liueth out of order, wyl ſoone come to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſion, &amp; people of the beſt fortune, but liue as the bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of their enemies.</p>
                              <p>The firſt Erector of the Romayn walles, was RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MVLVS, yet Roome was nothyng ſo much bound vnto him, for the envyronyng of her fayre buildynges, with ſtrong Bulwarkes, as in appoinctyng offices, ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and lawes among the people, to gouerne them in peace and proſperytie: This Romulus, (that Roome might proſper,) haſtened the death of his Brother RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MVS, an Act (ſimply) conſidered by Nature, very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, and the vengeance of deteſtable crueltie: but the ſeditious diſpoſition of Remus well po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred, neceſſytie approoued the ſeuerytie of ROMVLVS, to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Iuſtice. The loue we owe to our Parents, ought to be very reuerent and great, becauſe thei gaue vs lyfe: to our brethren, naturall, becauſe of preuytie in blood: to our frends,<note place="margin">Men ar more bound to the common-wealth then to Parentes.</note> affectionat, becauſe vertue or benefit is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foundation: But the loue we owe vnto our Countrey, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth vs to breake all theſe bandes of affection, in preſentyng the deereſt frends, offending againſt the Weale-publique: yea, in the ſeruice therof, to make it appeare, that the prodigall ſpoylles of our liues, giueth contempt vnto Death: That Examples of Kynges and Capital Maieſtrates, in this duetie, may be Samplers of Vertue vnto the inferiour Subiectes of Roome, I giue you to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, how Kyng LYCVRGVS went into (voluntary) exile, that his good Lawes, might haue long continuance among the Lacedemonians. Kyng CODRVS (wilfully) ran vpon his owne Daughter, (only) vpon a Propheſie, that the ſame ſhould deliuer his Countrey from inuaſion. AVCVRVS, Kyng
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20399:14"/> MYDAS Son of PHRIGIA, hauing knowledge that the yre of the Goddes, would not be pacified, vntil a liuing ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leapt into a great gaping gulph of the earth which ouerthrew many houſes, and dyd much hurt in the Countrey: The Kyngs Sonne, ANCVRVS, I ſay, leaſt ſome ſhould preuent him, (haſtely) kyſſed the King his father, his wife and frends, and (couragiouſly) leaped into this Gulph. What need we further ſearch then the Monumentes of Noble Romaynes: CVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIVS, dyd the like valiant deed of Ancurus. MV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIVS SCEVOLE, in diſguiſed Habyte, entred (alone) the Hetruryan Camp, to ſtay their kyng, who (daungerouſly) aſſaulted Rome. GAIVS MARI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VS, to ouercome the fierce Cymbrians, ſacrificed his deerely beloued Daughter CALPHVRNIA: Death was the certaine ende of al theſe enterpiſes: but theſe Noble perſonages, weare wondrous vncertaine, whither their Deathes ſhould rydde their Countreyes from daungers, or no: But Louers of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes proſperitie, maketh neither doubts nor delayes, where great peryll asketh preſent ſuccour: But, you wyll (peraduenture) ſaye, that you are redy to ſpende your lyues, your landes and Goods, to with-ſtande for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Hoſtilytie, or Domeſticall ennemies: If you ſo ſay, and doo ſo, Dutie challengeth al this, and wiſdome wylleth a deeper foreſight: It is a work of more thank to preſerue health, then to cure Sickneſſe, for, payn and griefe (onely) commendeth Medicine: euen-ſo, effuſion of innocent bloode, burnyng of Cytties, and rauiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Virgins, are the effectes of moſt glorious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtes: And truely, he that will giue cauſe of ſedition, though hee after dooth his vttermoſt to ſuppreſſe the
<pb facs="tcp:20399:15"/> ſame, is lyke vnto hym that doth (wilfully) ſurfet, that Phiſicke may heale hym: Your exceſſiue Coueitouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is example of the lyke miſchiefe: yea, this double daunger dependeth thereon: By the ſame, you vndoe the Gentlemen, whiche are the Beautie of Rome, and the ſtrength of the Empyre: For (al-be-it) lawe-leſſe Wolues wyll ſcarre Sheepe, yet maymed men, incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage Cowardes. Your aboundaunce, can not defende Forreigne Inuaſion, when the Gentlemens hartes are nipped with want: nay, it is to be feared, that Enuie and Neceſſytie, will make them to ioyne with the Enemie, to be reuenged of your Cruelties, or too be relieued of your ſuperfluyties.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>HEREWITH, the Multitude cried out, alowde: <hi>Accurſed be he, and vnworthie the name of a Citizyn of</hi> Rome, <hi>that, by vnſatiable Coueitouſnes and Vſurie, ſeeketh this publique delolution: what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is thus (vnlawfully) gotten, ſhalbe reſtored backe: Hereafter, ſuch vnprofitable members, ſhal be bridled:</hi> Liue vertuous Emperour, <hi>and what lack ye finde in vs, refourme it, and we wyll obey you and he that doth reſiſt, let him be ſlaine, and buried in</hi> Tyber: <hi>Your vertue hath reſtored vs to lyfe, that we are dead: vnto Lybertie, that were in thraldom: vnto Honour, that were diſhonoured. In Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, you be our Father, whome we well reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: by free election, our Emperour, whom we wil obay: &amp; in wiſdome our ſoundeſt Iudge, whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels, we wil execute, as generall Lawes. ¶Hereat, the Emperour releated, and with much paine, retayned the teares of his eyes, and (in the ende) comforted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this Concluſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="oration">
                              <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20399:15"/>
                              <head>The Conclusion of Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ANDERS <hi>Oration, to the Cittizyns</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>I Am right glad, that your Proteſtation declareth, that you yet hold ſome por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Vertue: which giueth vs hope, that the renown of this Noble Realme, begunne by Romulus, ſhall not ende in you: And if you be conſtant in this affection, we truſt, right ſhortly to make the Fame therof equall in eſtimation, with the Raignes of any of our Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours. And now, I haue fownd agayne your old name wherby I wyll call you.</p>
                              <p>Ye Children and Succeſſours of the vertuous Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes. I ſay, you victorious people, braunches of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus, ſubduers of Realmes, patternes of vertue, and proweſſe to all the world, mittigate your couetous ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, abandon exceſſiue Vſurie, exceede not the boundes of your popular ſtate, be charitable, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful vnto your owne Countrey-men, where their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie may be relieued with your abundance: Be you aſhamed, that labourers, and rude people, ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne you of crueltie, for deſtroying of your Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (the chiefe ornament, and defence of this noble Cittie.) Remember, that if the ſtate of Senators do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caye, the moſt vertuous of the Gentlemen are elected in their places: So you, that ſhall equall them in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue (for your ſubſtance onely cannot make you gentle) ſhall be aduaunced vnto the ſtate of Gentlemen, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your demerits.</p>
                              <pb facs="tcp:20399:16"/>
                              <p>Nowe haue we no more to ſay vnto you, but applye your ſelues to the auncient and moſt laudable orders, as we ſhal indeuour our ſelues, by example &amp; diligence, to bring this Citie againe vnto perfection.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVHen the good Emperor had thus ended his Oration, he cauſed diuers of the graueſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizyns, to attend hym at his Pallace, where he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, that by ſecrete inquirie, they ſhould learne how many Cittyzyns, by Vſurie, or other corrupte bargaynyng, had (abſolute poſſeſſion, or Morguage of the Gentlemens Landes: and to certifye, (bothe) the names of the Vſerers, and the Gentlemen ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed. Vppon whoſe certificate, he dealed with the Creditors of the Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beſtowyng a great portion of money out of his owne Treaſurie, tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes a generall agreement: as in the ende, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that the Creditors, ſhuld receiue the reſidue of their Debtes, by a yearely pention oute of the Gentlemens Landes: By whiche Newes, their Poſterytie might recouer, what their vnthriftineſſe had waſted. The Noble Emperour, hauynge brought to paſſe this hye benefite, for the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of</hi> Rome, <hi>with the poſſeſſion therof: in this lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng Oration, he inſtructed them in the Dueties of Gentlemen, and (mildely) reprehended the Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of their Reputation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="oration">
                              <pb n="11" facs="tcp:20399:16"/>
                              <head>
                                 <hi>The Emperour Alexander</hi> his Oration, to the Gentle men of Rome.</head>
                              <p>GEntlemen of Rome, by the name of Gentlemen I ſalute you, as Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie Title of your Aunceſtours vertues, which I hope will alwayes remayne in your hearts: How-be-it, too exceſſiue prodigalitie, hath much waſted your liuings, and impayred your credit. But with the blame of your lauiciouſnes, I am bound (by the woorking of pittie) to ſhew the cauſe thereof: Which (although it bee no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe in Iuſtice) yet it iuſtly moueth commiſeration. The examples of our predeceſſors wickedneſſe, is more liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye expreſſed in your workes, then may be ſhowen by my wordes, and I hope, his worthie confuſion, will be cauſe of your ſpeedy amendment. Yet, I hold it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, to laie before your eyes, the monſtrous euilles, which you haue learned of your late Emperour Heli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ogabalus: that, comparing his wretched ende, with his wicked raigne, feare may reforme, what our louing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection wiſheth to be amended in you.</p>
                              <p>This veſſel of abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo exceeded in pride, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> top to toe, he was attired in cloth of golde, pearle, &amp; pretious-ſtones,<note place="margin">Vyces of Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yogabalus</note> &amp; neuer wore any garment more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> once, from his bed chamber, vnto the place where hee mounted vnto his Coch, the walles were decked wyth tapeſtrie full of greate pearles, and pretious ſtones. The waie as he went, was ſtrewed with golde and ſiluer, as one diſdayning to treade vppon earth lyke other men.
<pb facs="tcp:20399:17"/> His Charyot was ſometyme drawen with tame Lions, ſometimes with Elephantes, and ſometimes with mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous faire Women. The Kinges which he drewe off his fingers, hee neuer put on againe. The veſſels of golde and ſiluer, wherein he was ſerued, was euermore the ſees of his ſeruitors. Suche huge prodigalitie was ioined with his incomparable pride. His gluttonie, &amp; voluptuouſnes was ſo great, as neere the Sea, his whole houſhold was fed with moſt daintie fowles: and beeing farre within lande, they were all ſerued with all maner of fiſhes, by Poſte brought alyue from the Sea: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time he had for a generall ſeruice, paſties of Peacockes toonges, other whyle Partridges egges, the heades of Popiniayes, Feſauntes, and the moſt daintieſt Byrdes: Neither was this ſuperfluitie alone vpon the Tables in his owne Pallace, but in ſelfe ſame manner, his Lyons, Gray-hounds, and other Dogs of pleaſure were fed. He ſo much eſteemed of thinges that were deare and rare, that hearing there was but one Phaenix in the worlde, hee offered twoo thowſand Markes to haue it to hys Dinner.</p>
                              <p>His lecherie was ſo vnſatiable, and withalſo vnclean, as common ciuilitie forbiddeth the report.</p>
                              <p>His Puſalanimitie was ſuch, as he ſtudied how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a woman, and of moſte notorious Strumpets, and Bawdes, hee erected a Senate, and in a Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll, for the no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>ce, hee made vnto them manie Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and called them his Companions, and fellowe Souldiers.</p>
                              <p>That vice might haue no ſtaye, nor vertue anie paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20399:17"/> he gaue free Charters to all men to vſe all manner of villanie. And Sabinus, Vlpianus, and other learned and reuerent Iudges hee baniſhed from the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Iuſtice.</p>
                              <p>He cruelly put to death many worthie perſonages, &amp; amongſt the people many times let looſe Lions, Beares, and other cruell Beaſtes. In fine, when his monſtrous pryde, prodigallitie, and lecherie, had conſumed all his own treaſure, neceſſitie &amp; a naughtie diſpoſition, made him to ſell the offices of Iuſtice. But his owne familiar Seruantes and Souldiers, wearie of his abhominations, ſlew him: &amp; drawing his horrible Carren with hooks through the Cittie, they tyed him to a ſtone of greate waight, and threw him into Tyber, to the end ſo vile a bodie ſhould neuer be buried: Yet, your owne eies are Iudges that I ſay the truth. His death and funerals was as vile and filthie, as, what I haue ſaide of his life, was ſumptuous and rich.</p>
                              <p>I haue laide the miſerie of his death before your eyes, that you ſhould expell the vices of his life forth of your harts. It was the due of his beaſtlines, and will be the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of your inſolent liuing without amendment.</p>
                              <p>You are yet yong, &amp; by proweſſe may recouer more then you haue by prodigalitie waſted: A vertuous end repaireth the diſhonors of a vicious life: But ſhame ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, when lewd men are dead. A prodigall and volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous humor, I know is hardly purged, bicauſe the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhments are many and ſweete. But when I conſider, that you are Gentlemen, I ſtraightwaies hope, that you will eaſilye ſubdue theſe affections. There is nothyng more pretious to man then life, nor nothing more fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then death.</p>
                              <pb facs="tcp:20399:18"/>
                              <p>Yet the noble Romaine Gentlemen your aunceſtors, in actions of honour, preferred the laſt before the firſt. If you be heires of their vertues, Vſurers cannot pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe that patrimonie: And therefore, great is our hope, that you will bridle meane affections, when they contemned the greateſt. ROMVLVS with a weake ſtrength, and inuincible courage, firſt buylded this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Citie, and of his name ſhee is called to this daye Roome. Numa Pompilius that ſucceeded him, both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged the boundes, and ſtrengthened her, with manie good lawes and orders: And in proceſſe of time, the wiſdome of the Maieſtrates, and valiancie of her Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, made Rome, The Soueraigne of Citties, the Beautie of the earth, and Empreſſe of rhe whole world: And ſo to this daye had remained, had not the horrible vices of her Emperors Nero, Caligula, Domitian, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus, and Heliogabalus, eclipſed her glorie, and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted her people with abhominations: But vertue is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to perfect more then vice hath deformed. We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the Gods, that on our part there may bee no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faulte, as wee earneſtly deſite reformation in you: And then (no doubt) Rome ſhall ſhortlye haue her auncient honour, and you the reputation of Romulus heires. This badge of pryde,<note place="margin">
                                    <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                                       <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                    </gap> apparell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                                       <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                    </gap>yee for ſage players</note> Brauerie in apparell, is neceſſarie for baſe perſons, that publiquely in open Theaters, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente the perſonages of Emperoures, Kinges, Dukes, and ſuch Heroycall Eſtates: For that they haue no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meane to perfourme their action. But the magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Gentleman, carrieth honor in his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinance, and not countenance in his Garments.</p>
                              <p>CICERO diſcouered the Haughtineſſe of Caeſar in his fore-heade.</p>
                              <pb n="13" facs="tcp:20399:18"/>
                              <p>ASTIAGES, ſaw a Kyngly minde in CYRVS, although, hee were armed with a Sheepehooke: man maketh the Habyt, and not Habyt a man.</p>
                              <p>Drunkenneſſe and Glotonie,<note place="margin">Dronkennes and glotney, greatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graceth a gentleman.</note> are fowle maymes too Honour, and the greateſt deformytie in a Gentleman:</p>
                              <p>Call Alexander, the great, to witneſſe, who, after hee had conquered (almoſte) all the whole Worlde, with the Swoord, conquered hym-ſelfe with a Wine-potte: So that, it is a queſtion, whither he receiued more Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, in ouer commyng the mighty Darius, of Perſia, or Diſhonor, by beyng ſubdued, by the Perſians Vices: If I were a Iudge, Alexander, ſhould find a ſeueare Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement: for, by his valiancie, he did but conquer his ennemies, and in his drunkenneſſe, he ſlew his frendes, and haſtened his owne death.</p>
                              <p>Prodigalytie, is ſo ſharpe a vengeance,<note place="margin">The venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Prodigalitie</note> as there nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no Lawe to chaſtiſe the Prodigall man, he doth ſo ſeuerely puniſh him-ſelfe. Epicharidus, the Athenian, in ſixe Dayes conſumed his Patrimonie, and al his lyfe after, liued a Begger.</p>
                              <p>Paſicirus, kyng of Cyprus, firſt (prodigallie) ſpent his Treaſure, afterwards, ſould his Realme, and (laſtly) died (miſerablie) in the Cittie of Amathuntus,</p>
                              <p>The prodigall Cleops, Kyng of Egypte, was driuen vnto ſuch neceſſitie, as he was faine to liue of the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt vſe of his Daughters bodie.</p>
                              <p>If prodigalitie bring Kings to this exigent, who haue manie ſupplies; it ſpeedilye ruineth the richeſt Subiect: yea, (which is worſt) their recouerie is as vncertaine, as their vndooing is certaine: For by colour of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uennewes, they runne in debt the triple value of theyr
<pb facs="tcp:20399:19"/> Landes. You Gentlemen of Rome, knowe this better by experience, then by my information, you feele the ſmart of prodigalitie: by ryot you were dtyuen to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage your Lands, and had loſt the ſame, and your ſelues, had not our liberalitie redeemed both: our louing care to preuent, that followeth after prodigalitie, whiche is this perillous daunger:</p>
                              <p>Men, beyng (by prodigalytie) Enemies of their owne and poſteryties proſpetytie: by want and Neceſſytie, become Enemies of their Countreyes peace and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, I ſaie, feare of this miſchiefe, and loue of your weldoynge, hath repurchaſed your Landes: receyue of vs, the Poſſeſſion therof, as a Cogniſance of our loue, and deſyre that you maye flooryſh: Keepe your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour with your Landes, leaſt our ſeuere diſpleaſure, be heaped vpon your vndoynges: Lette vertuous Polly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Documents be your ſtuddie: ſee that your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, bee Feates of Chiualrye: vſe your handes, to the managynge of Armes,<note place="margin">The diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing.</note> and not your Fyngers to the trippynge of Dice, a Paſtyme, ſo villanous, that (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandinge) the loſſe be doubtfull, the diſhonour is certaine.</p>
                              <p>GOBILON, the Athenian, beyng ſent Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, to make League with the Corrynthians, who, findyng the Gouernours of Corrynth, playinge at the Dice, departed without diſpatch of his buſines: ſaying, <hi>He would not ſtaine the Glorye of the</hi> Spartianes, <hi>in makyng League with Dicers.</hi> The Kyng of the Perſians, ſent goulden Dice to kynge Demetrius, for a reproache of his Lightneſſe. Cicero, in the Senate-houſe, put Anthonius to ſcilence, in ſayinge, he was a Dicer: And (truely) ſo infamous a paſtime, neither
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20399:19"/> beſeemeth the Grauitie of the Magiſtrate, nor Honor of a Gentleman, for that the gaine, is loaden with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt practiſes, and the loſſe, with vnquiet paſſions.</p>
                              <p>Learn by the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinencie of the mightie Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, &amp; the noble Romain Scipio, to ſubdue carnal affections:<note place="margin">worthye examPls of continencie</note> the one, hauyng (by fortune of warre, the poſſeſſion of kyng Darius Wyfe, the moſte beautifull Ladie of all ASIA, he neither ſuffred him-ſelfe, to bee conquered by her beautie, nor the Queene to bee diſhonoured by his victorie. The other, hauyng lyke Aduauntage of the Paragon of Spayne, with the ſemblable vertue, vanquiſhed his Affections.</p>
                              <p>On the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie part, know ye, that Rome (of late) hath had more Emperours brought vnto the Sepulture, by Lecherie, then in many hundred yeares before, by the Launce. Gentlemen, my Kinſmen and Companions. I admoniſh you from naughtineſſe, by the falles of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, kynges, and Heroycall Eſtates: that you maye knowe, in the puniſhment of vice, the Goddes, neither feare nor ſpare, the mightieſt of men. On the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie parte I counſell you to goodneſſe, by the Counſell of our dignitie, aſſuring you, by the exerciſe of Vertue, meaner then Gentlemen, become Emperours of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. Wee haue no more to ſaye: but that the Goddes impreſſe in your hartes, the counſell we haue blowen into your eares, and that your Emperour A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander, maye beholde Rome, Rome agayne: And you (Gentlemen of Rome) worthye the reputation of your Noble Aunceſtors.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20399:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVHen the good Emperor, had ended his Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: the Gentlemen, ouercome with the Princely fauour and affection of</hi> Alexander, <hi>as (alſo) voounded, with the knowledge of their former laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiouſneſſe, diſcouered a great diſmaye of Spirite:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the ende, with abaſed Countenaunces, vppon their knees, they humbly acknowledged his grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous benefits: confeſſed their owne vnworthyneſſe, and faithfullie promiſed, to obay his fatherly Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes. The good Emperour, then, demaunded, yf they would be contented, that their Debts ſhuld be paide by yearely pentions out of their Landes, and if they woulde (ſparingely) liue, accordyng vnto the proportion of the reſt? They al aunſwerd with one voyce: Yea (noble Emperor) els were we accurſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>¶<hi>The prudent</hi> Alexander, <hi>hauing by theſe graue Orations, ſounded the inclynations, of the three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of <hi>Rome. vz. The Senators: The Gentlemen, and the Citizyns:</hi> forſook not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage of the peoples good diſpoſitions, but whyle the Vertue of his wiſe Counſelles was workyng in their hartes, he, with the Aduice of his graue Senators, deuiſed many good Lawes, for the abandonyng and baniſhment of Vices foorth of the Citie: aſſuryng himſelfe, that where Diſcipline was wanting, the ſowndeſt cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, purged not corrupt maners: ſo that, to the loue which his Affabylitie had wonne, he ioyned dread, through ſeuere executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, of theſe profitable lawes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20399:20"/>
                     <head>
                        <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Lawes, Pains, and <hi>Penalties, ſet downe by</hi> Alexander Seuerus, to puniſh Offenders againſt the Weale-publique.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In primis</hi> For that the Tauarnes, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing-houſes, &amp; the Stewes,<note place="margin">Tauernes ſtewes anb dicing houſes</note> were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Nurſes of all vices, and the Sanctuaries of vicious perſons, he ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all ſuch, as were of euyll fame: ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That, if the Owners could not liue, but vpon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ndoynge of others, it were reaſon, they ſhould ſtarue, by the neceſſytie of their idle bryngyng vp.</p>
                     <p>¶<hi>Item:</hi> He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that in the Tauarns,<note place="margin">Open bothes in Tauernes.</note> there ſhould be no other, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> open Boothes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the <hi>Cenſors,</hi> might ſee the behauiors &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people that haunted them.</p>
                     <p>¶<hi>Item:</hi> He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, that no Gentleman,<note place="margin">Gentlemen, for bidden, Tauernes</note> 
                        <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne,</hi> ſhould reſorte to any of theſe Houſes, vppon paine, to loſe the name of a Gentleman.</p>
                     <p>¶<hi>Item:</hi> He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, that no Senator, ſhould haue more then fower Diſſhes at his Dinner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        <note place="margin">Glottony and Dronke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</note> nor Gentleman, or Citizyn, more then three: And that, the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people, ſhould feed (onely) of one Diſh, of fiſh or fleſh: ſaying, that Glotonie and Drunkeneſſe, not (onely) conſumed the wealth of the Weale pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blique, but alſo, the health of the people.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20399:21"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20399:21"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20399:22"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Limitation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Apparell</note>¶<hi>Item:</hi> He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Romain,</hi> ſhuld haue more then three Sutes of Apparel: one, for Ordinarie dayes: one other for Feſtiuall tymes: and the thyrd, for the entertainme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Ambaſſadors: alleadging, that all theſe were neceſſary, &amp; what ſo euer was more, was ſuperfluous. This Lawe was alſo ſet downe by <hi>Philip le Bel,</hi> to reforme the pride of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and by <hi>Fardinando,</hi> King of <hi>Arra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to huſbandry the ſmal pentions of the Knightes of the Lande, which order he hym ſelfe erected.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Dyce made bond ſlaues</note>¶<hi>Item</hi> He enacted, if any Gentleman Romane, or Citizin <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>ome,</hi> by playing at Dice, hau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting of Tauarns, or any other vnthrifrie exerciſe, had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his patrimonie &amp; ſubſtance, &amp; was indebted more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was able to ſatiſfie: that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it ſhuld be lawfull for the Creditor, to take the parte offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, &amp; to hold him as his bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d-ſlaue, ſo long as the ſeruice &amp; labour of his body were thought ſufficient for his debt. Were this a lawe in England, I feare mee, at this preſent, we ſhuld haue more Gentlemen bond-men, then Ye men truſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Lymitation but vſurie</note>¶<hi>Item,</hi> For that Vſury was the decay of a huge nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, he enacted, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no Vſerer, ſhuld take (after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>putation of their money, more then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> allowance, of .iii.li, i. <hi>s.</hi> for a. C. ii, for a yeare. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he which refuſed to deliuer his monie at this rate, ſhuld from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cefoorth, be held vnworthie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of a <hi>Romain,</hi> or to take any benefit by the Weale-publique. But ſhuld, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                        <hi>Cehſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s,</hi> be departed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin, &amp;, for euer, after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>huld be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> on the cryme of Ingratitude.</p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:20399:22"/>
                     <p>¶<hi>Item,</hi> From hence forth,<note place="margin">Mony lent to dice players without hope to be reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</note> no neceſſitie be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in them that conſume their ſubſtaunce, in Dice playing, outragious expences or lechery: who ſo euer lendeth to them, let it be at his peril &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope of remedie. But vnto him whom peruerſe fortune, long ſickeneſſe, ſeruice, frendeſhip, theeues,<note place="margin">Aſſinement of Creditors for diſtreſſed perſones.</note> or oppreſſors haue brought vnto pouertie: If any ſuch come vnto the Prouoſt of the Citie, and declare his neceſſitie, and whereof it proceeded, vppon the oath of one Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ator, and two honeſt Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moners, that his words are true, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prouoſt ſhal aſſigne one rich man of the Citie to lend him a po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>n of mony, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king aſſuraunce for the payment thereof, for the gayne before limited.</p>
                     <p>¶<hi>Item,</hi> He enacted, that if any Citizin of <hi>Rome,</hi> were found idle, by the ſpace of one whole day, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,<note place="margin">Idle perſons ſet a worke</note> vpon a Feſtiuall. Day, hauyng no lawful nor approoued excuſe: that then, he ſhould be firſt whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and after, by the <hi>Conſeruators,</hi> he ſhould be ſet to the trade that he was of, and for euery day, that he was openly ſeene, to be idle, the perſon, to whom he was committed, for one month, ſhould ſet him to what labour he pleaſed, as his ſlaue or bond-man, giuyng him, meat and drinke, onely.</p>
                     <p>¶<hi>Item:</hi> He commaunded,<note place="margin">For Corrup-of victuales</note> that the Controw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the Markettes, ſhould be honeſt men, and not coueitous: and (for the auoydyng of the Infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) that they ſhould diligently forſee, that the Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualles, which were ſould, ſhould be ſweete and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome for to be eaten.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20399:23"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Late ſappors,</note>¶<hi>Item:</hi> To auoide cauſe of Infection, and horrible Diſeaſes, he prohibited Ingurgitations, Bankets, late Suppers and longe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ayſome occupations.</note>¶<hi>Item:</hi> He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, that men of corrupt and noyſome Occupations, ſhould dwell out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon paſſage of the people: And that the ſtreetes of the Cities, ſhould be kepte very cleanly and ſweete.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Sweete keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of baynes</note>¶<hi>Item,</hi> He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded that the Baynes, by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete keepers, ſhould be kept very neate and ſweet, that neither the eye nor Noſe, ſhuld find any thyng vnpleaſant or noyſome. By which cleanlineſſe, <hi>Rome</hi> was preſerued from ſundry ſickneſſes which (vndoubtedly) do grow of corrupt exhalations, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of mennes bodies.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Hoſpitals for poore people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </note>¶<hi>Item,</hi> Of his own charge, he builded three Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalles, to relieue the Aged, blind, decreaped, and other poore people, infected w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vncureable Diſeaſes</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Cure for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſed Vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bondes.</note>¶<hi>Item:</hi> He commaunded, that vnto a nomber of yong diſeaſed vacabunds, there ſhuld be miniſtred, a thin Diet, an exceſſiue labor, and cleanly lodging: ſaying that the contrarie, were the cauſes of their Diſeaſes, and, therfore, this the moſt hopefull Medicine, to recouer their health.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Prouiſion of Corne,</note>¶<hi>Item:</hi> He commaunded, that all the Forfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which were leuied, vpon the Gooddes of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders againſt the Lawe, ſhould be imployed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Corne for the prouiſion of the poore.</p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:20399:23"/>
                     <p>¶<hi>Item:</hi> He commaunded, that no man ſhould weare in his Apparayle, no maner of Stuffe,<note place="margin">A lawe for The ſetting of Poore people a worke.</note> other then was made within the Cittie of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The lyke Statute was eſtabliſhed in all the Cyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Italye:</hi> by meanes wherof, <hi>Rome</hi> and all the other Cyties were ſtoared of good Workemen, and the poore people, no excuſe for Idlenes.</p>
                     <p>¶<hi>Item:</hi> He commaunded,<note place="margin">Vitayling and bordell-houſes</note> that in vittailing and Bordel-houſes, the Doores ſhould not be open from the Sun-ſettyng vntyll the Sun-riſyng: by which Pollycie, the <hi>Conſeruators</hi> knewe, what manner of people repayred vnto them.</p>
                     <p>¶<hi>Item:</hi> Euery Cittizyn, was ſtraightly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, to eate or drinke in any Tauerne,<note place="margin">Cyttizyns for bydden. Tauernes.</note> or vittayling Houſe: whiche Houſes, were (only) tollerated, for the intertainment of Straungers, which repayred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Cyttie about lawfull buſineſſe,</p>
                     <p>¶<hi>Item:</hi> He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, that all corrupt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull Bargayners,<note place="margin">Corrupt and deceatfull Bargayners. Puniſhed as Petty theaues</note> ſhould bee puniſhed with the Whyp, as Theeues, that ſtole priuylie, without any violence: affyrming, that it was but a fantaſie, and a laughyng-matter, to make a difference, betweene ſtealyng and deceitfull bargayninge. But, were this a Lawe with vs, we ſhuld haue more weeping in <hi>London,</hi> then laughynge in three of the greateſt Shiers of <hi>Englande.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>¶<hi>Item:</hi> He commaunded:<note place="margin">vnequall comparyſons</note> that if any bace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicioned perſon, by the preſumption of welth, ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:20399:24"/> make any ſawcie compariſon with any Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Romayne: immediatly, the ſaid Franklyne, ſhould become the Gentlemans Bondſlaue, with whome he compared, vntil the ſaid Franklyn, had made the Gentleman his ſuperiour, aſwell in wealth, as dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytie: And this Lawe hindered many quarrelles, which (otherwiſe) would haue growen of vnequall comparyſons.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Playes abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhed</note>
                        <hi>Item:</hi> He commaunded, that the Playes, called <hi>Florales</hi> and <hi>Luberalos,</hi> and the beaſtly Ceremonies of <hi>Iſis,</hi> ſhuld be baniſhed and aboliſhed, as the moſt venymous Alectiues and ſtyrrers of Lecherie,</p>
                     <p>¶<hi>Item:</hi> He ordayned, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any man were founde playing at the Dice,<note place="margin">Diceplayers.</note> he ſhuld be taken, for a frantick or a natural foole, which could not gouerne himſelfe and his gooddes and lande, ſhould be committed to ſage and diſcreete Gouernours, vntyll he were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine enabled by the Senate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Vnto theſe Lavves, vvas <hi>added this Confyrmation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>¶Theſe Lawes, decreed by the Senate, enacted by the people, comfirmed by the imperiall Maieſtie, be (for euer) eſtabliſhed: and (neuer) by anye other Lawe, Cuſtome or Ordinance, be abolyſhed. And who, that with violence, reſiſteth againſt them, let him be taken for a Rebell and Ennemie vnto the Weale-publique.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:20399:24"/>
                     <head>Of the great VViſdome of ALEXANDER, <hi>in electyng of Graue</hi> Counſellers, Officers, and Admy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrators of Iuſtice.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THE</hi> Noble and vertuous Emperour (prudently) forſawe, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereſt lawes, were (without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution) but like vnto painted Fire, which giueth no heat: or (as the Phyloſopher, <hi>Cleanthes</hi> ſayth:) Lyke vnto Cobwebs, through which, the Hornets breake when the ſmall Flies are intangled. And (truely) without due Adminiſtration, law is like to a Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwoorde, the edge wherof, ſmiteth the poore, and the blunt backe, the higher powers. But to auoyd this parcialytie: the good <hi>Alexander,</hi> made choyce of ſuch worthy Maieſtrates, as (playnly) refuted this <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime</hi> of <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Amor et odium, et proprium commodum,</l>
                        <l>Semper facient Iudices, non cognoſcere verum.</l>
                        <l>¶In Englyſh, thus:</l>
                        <l>¶<hi>Loue, Hate, and priuate gayne,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>From vpright trueth, the Iudge doth alwayes ſtraine</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                     <p>None of theſe Affections, could (neyther) blinde their eyes, nor binde their handes: They meaſured Iuſtice, neither by the mightineſſe nor meaneneſſe of the Perſon, but by the equitie of the cauſe: and it ſtoode them in hande, to deale thus vprightly: for if any corruption were founde in their Iudgements, the Emperour himſelfe, did (ſeuere) Iuſtice vppon the vniuſt Maieſtrate, that abuſed his Auctorytie,
<pb facs="tcp:20399:25"/> and iniured the people: let <hi>Vetronius Turinus;</hi> be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, for many.</p>
                     <p>This <hi>Turinus,</hi> was a man of much Honour, great learning and wiſdome: and for many vertues, was of the Emperour (ſingularly) fauoured: but, abuſing the Emperour and his own good fortune, vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of often and familiar conference w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                        <hi>Alexander,</hi> he receiued many Brybes to obtaine great ſutes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue his power to compaſſe: whiche beyng prooued agaynſt him, the Emperours ſentence was: That in the Market place, he ſhould bee bownde vnto a Stake, and with a Smoake of greene Stickes and wette Stubble, ſhould be ſmoothred to death: And duryng the tyme of his Execution, he commaunded a Beadell to crye: <q>With Fume let him die, that Fumes hath ſould.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus, no knowen Offender, eſcaped the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his ſeuerytie: and (which won him as much loue, as his Iuſtice did feare,) he incouraged &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted good &amp; vertuous men, with many great gifts and fauours.</p>
                     <p>¶ That <hi>Rome</hi> might proſper, by the confuſion of vice:<note place="margin">Conſeruators and their chardge.</note> Firſt, he ordayned (accordyng to the counſell of <hi>PLATO,</hi>) three-ſcore graue perſons, which were named, <hi>CONSERVATORS of the Weale-publique:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Education of children.</note> for euery Tribe had two: <hi>Roome</hi> beynge deuided into thirtie Tribes: whoſe Office, was (chiefly) to ſee, that the children of the <hi>Romains,</hi> were well brought vp and inſtructed, accordyng vnto the capacities of their wits, from the Age of .vii. yeres, vnto .xvi. yeares: &amp; that, in their Paſtimes, playes and recreations, were nothyng diſhoneſt.</p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:20399:25"/>
                     <p>¶ <hi>Item:</hi> That the Maidens, duryng the ſaid Age,<note place="margin">Education of maydens</note> were brought vp in ſhamefaſtnes, humblenes, and the exerciſe of Huſwifrye: and that they ſhould not be ſeene foorth of their Fathers-houſes, but (only) in the Temples.</p>
                     <p>¶ <hi>Item:</hi> their charge was,<note place="margin">Riotous houſe holders</note> to controwle Howſe-houlders of euery degree, if there were fownde any exceſſe in their fare, or coſt vpon their owne, or their Wyues Apparayle, more then by the Lawes, was limitted: or if they were Company-keepers with any riotous or diſhoneſt perſon.</p>
                     <p>¶ <hi>Item:</hi> Twice (by the weeke) they were bownd to make Preſentment of the Diſorders whiche they fownd, vnto the Prouoſt of the Cittie,<note place="margin">Preſentation, twice by the weeke.</note> reſeruing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them-ſelues, the education of the Children: which they-them-ſelues reformed, by giuing of ſharpe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monytion vnto their Parentes.</p>
                     <p>¶ The Prouoſt puniſhed ſuche,<note place="margin">Prouoſt of al the Citty.</note> as offended in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Articles, againſt the Statutes and Ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in ſuche caſes prouided.</p>
                     <p>¶ <hi>Item:</hi> The Emperour augmented the nomber of <hi>Praetors</hi> and <hi>Queſtors,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pretores and Queſtors</note> but appoin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ted euerye one a ſeuerall Charge.</p>
                     <p>¶ <hi>Item:</hi> He made choyce,<note place="margin">Puruiours of grayne</note> of very honeſt men to be Purueiours for grayne, but changed them euery yeare, leaſt, continuance corrupted their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20399:26"/>
                     <p>¶ <hi>Item:</hi> He apoincted Baylyffes, Receiuers, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiours, and ſuch like Officers, but fauoured them not, ſaying: they were neceſſarie euils: And if they haſtilie gathered much riches, he would take away al that they had. Telling them. <hi>Let it ſuffice, that you haue taken ſo long pleaſure with my goodes: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that you take not from other men vniuſtly, leaſt I be more angrie with you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>¶ <hi>Item:</hi> To be Iudges of theſe Officers, as alſo of the behauiours of all the people of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Cenſors, and their office.</note> ſauing the common people, were they <hi>Senatores, Gentlemen</hi> or <hi>Citizens.</hi> This prudent Emperour appointed two of his priuie Counſel, worthy and graue Senators, to be <hi>Cenſors</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe names were <hi>Fabius Sabinus,</hi> and <hi>Catillius Seuerus.</hi> The office of the <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,</hi> were to note the manners of euerie perſon, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the degree of the common people.</p>
                     <p>So that if a Knight, Iudge, or Senator, did any thing vnſeeming the Honour of their Degree, their charge was, to degrade hym of his office, or Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. In whiche, they vſed ſuche rigour, as no man might (lawfully) boaſt of fauor. In ſo much, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperors Pallace was not free from their iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. For they meeting with <hi>Aurelius Philippus,</hi> (who was ſometime the Emperours ſhoolmaſter, and after wrote his life) riding in a Chariot, looking to be ſaluted as a Senatour, they foorthwith execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an auncient law vpon the ſaid <hi>Philippus:</hi> which was, that no bond-man, although hee were manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed, ſhould be a Senatour: And at that time, it was lawful for no perſon vnder the degree of a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natour
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20399:26"/> to ride in a Chariot. <hi>Philippus</hi> was ſometime a bond-man, and therefore, for breach of this lawe, the <hi>Cenſors</hi> ſent him firſt to priſon, and after, forbad him to come to the Emperors pallace, but (onelie) a foot, and his copped Cappe vpon his head: which faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was onelie vſed of them that were enfranchiſed. Some of the Noble-men thought, the <hi>Cenſors</hi> dealt verie ſharplie with <hi>Philippus,</hi> conſidering, that hee was a man of much honeſtie, and great learning, and ſo certefied the Emperour. But the Emperour approoued their Iuſtice, and anſwered:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If the common wealth may euermore haue ſuch offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, in ſhort ſpace, there ſhall be found in Roome more men worthie to be Emperours, than I (at my firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming) found good Senators.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And vndoubtedlie, where the offences of the beſt are neuer pardoned, the worſt will amend for feare of extreeme vengeance. The proofe appeareth in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexanders</hi> gouernment: who (by the ſeuere executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lawes, ſo brideled the diſpoſitions of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, that it may be ſaide, they grew to be vertuous rather by cuſtome, then good inclination. Yea, it is written, that his ſeueritie thus much profited: As leading a great armie againſt <hi>Artaxerſes,</hi> the <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> ſaid, he had brought an armie of Senatours, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than of Soldiours, when at his comming to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Empire, the Senatours (manie of them) were as diſſolute as common Soldiers.<note place="margin">A wiſe polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander.</note> And one eſpeciall cautle hee vſed in the ſearche of mens behauiours, hee woulde manye tymes in diſguyſed habyte, with diuers others by hym eſpeciallye elected,
<pb facs="tcp:20399:27"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:20399:27"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb facs="tcp:20399:28"/> take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him the Office of the <hi>Cenſors:</hi> and in euery corner, he had (ſecretly) ſuche faythfull Explorers, as mens proper Houſes, were no Couerts for naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie practiſes, nor the Senat-houſe, for partial Iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes. And (by this Pollycie) he diſcouered many naughtie matters, beſides co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon treſpaſſes: as the Treaſon of <hi>Oninius,</hi> the falſe accuſation of <hi>Gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> by his Lybertines, or Copyholders: as (alſo) of the mortall mallice of <hi>Duillius</hi> and <hi>Gotta,</hi> towardes the ſaid <hi>Geminus.</hi> In ſo much, as the people, ſeyng nothyng that was euyl, could eſcape his vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, al men indeuored to do well, to purchaſe his fauour.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">King Henry the ſeuenth, Imitator of Alexanders gouernment.</note>THE (moſt Noble and prudent) Kynge, Kynge <hi>HENRY, the ſeuenth,</hi> the Queenes (moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maieſties Graundfather, and Roote of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landes</hi> happineſſe, was a true imitator, of this (moſt worthy) Emperours gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: by whoſe ſingular wiſdome, <hi>England,</hi> which at the beginning of his <hi>Raigne:</hi> was a deformed, and decreped Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealthe, by reaſon of the longe tyme of the Cyuyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warres which durynge ſyx Kinges Raignes made barrayne feildes, and fatt Churche-yardes) before his deathe, repoſſeſſed her Auncient Vertues, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown and proſperytie. So that it is a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this famous Realm is more bownd to eternize his glorious Memorie, in regarde of his Proweſſe, or Pollycie: when by the one, he planted Peace in her bowelles, and by the other, baniſhed warre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Terrytories. He knew, that to reforme ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered an eſtate, it was more needefull to execute, then to make Lawes: and (therfore) not truſtyng
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20399:28"/> the corruption of common Informers, who, for lucre or gain, attemptyng many vexations againſt poore men, and for feare, ſeeke to pleaſe the ritche:<note place="margin">Inclynation of Common Informers</note> he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the execution of the Penall Lawes, to the charge of theſe two worthie Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellers, fir <hi>Richard Empſon,</hi> Knight, and <hi>Richarde Dudley,</hi> Eſquier: who ſo ſeuerely chaſtened the rich and great Offenders, as they ſtirred the inconſtant co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munaltie, after the death of the vertuous <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſeuenth, to ſeeke their lyues: who had their willes, for feare of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, theaſe two worthie Maieſtrates weare beheaded: And (vndoubtedly) their deathes, is a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of as great vertue, as their liues, a Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Iuſtice: for the multitude,<note place="margin">The lewde affections, of Common people.</note> are the mortall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of their owne welfare, and frendes and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of their owne confuſion. One ſaid to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſthenes:</hi> The people ſpeaketh much good of you: Why? ſaide he: what hurt haue I done? As who ſhould ſay: they ſeldome praiſe, but ſuche as do euil: No Ethnicke, deſerued to lyue, better then <hi>Socrates,</hi> yet the people would haue hym dead. The <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> had a Lawe, euerie yeare, by the moſt voyces of the people, for ten yeares, to banyſh two of their principall Maieſtrates: On a tyme, a poore man, came with a white Paper in his hande to <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> the iuſt, and willed him to write: Baniſh <hi>Ariſtides.</hi> Why? (quoth he:) doeſt thou know <hi>Ariſtides?</hi> No: (quoth the other:) Hath <hi>Ariſtides</hi> done thee or any of thy friendes, hurte? Neither (quoth he) but I wyll haue <hi>Ariſtides</hi> baniſhed. The worthy <hi>Scipio</hi> was baniſhed by the people, whome he oft had ſaued.</p>
                     <p>I omyt <hi>Themiſtocles, Photion,</hi> &amp; many mo, whome
<pb facs="tcp:20399:29"/> Hiſtories record, to ſhewe the light Iudgementes of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons, <hi>Danté,</hi> the Italian Poet, ſaithful truely of them: it is ſeldome ſeene, that the people crye not:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Viua la mia morte, innoia la mia vita:</hi> Let liue my death: let die my lyfe: Yea, thoſe great eſtates, that ſeek to pleaſe the people, for the moſt parte, haue had the endes of enemies to their Countrey.</p>
                     <p>When <hi>Cicero ſawe that Caeſar</hi> was in hye fauour with the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> he cryed out: <hi>It is great pitie, that the affabilitie of Caeſar, ſhould be the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the Weale-publique.</hi> And (truely) <hi>Cicero,</hi> propheſied rightly: for, by their fauour, <hi>Caeſar</hi> iudged the Iudgementes of the Senate, and ſent the good and graue <hi>Cato</hi> to Priſon, whoſe vertues, obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned reuerence of the woorſt liuers.</p>
                     <p>But (notwithſtandyng) the Affections of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, coueiteth their owne vndoynges, yet their incouragement proceedeth of greater capacyties:</p>
                     <p>And (therfore) the redy way to keepe them in awe, is (ſeuerely) to punyſh their Chief-taynes.</p>
                     <p>In all tumultes, it is (euidently) ſeene, that if their Captaynes yelde, they ronne away: if their Incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragers be diſmayde, they ſing, <hi>Peccaui:</hi> do Iuſtice vpon the great Offenders, and the meaner wyll ſoone amend: <hi>Alexander</hi> (in his Gouernment) found it true: who, in the Execution of the Lawes, made no difference of perſons: ſaue, that, to the inferiour people, he was (euermore) moſt mercifull.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20399:29"/>
                  <p>AN ADDITION: OR TOVCHSTONE for the Time: expoſyng the <hi>dain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gerous Miſchiefes, that the Dicyng Howſes (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly</hi> called) <hi>Ordinarie Tables,</hi> and other (like) <hi>Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuaries</hi> of Iniquitie, do dayly breede:</p>
                  <p>Within the Bovvelles of the famous-CITIE of LONDON.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By</hi> George Wherſtones, <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Imprinted at London, by Richarde Iones.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20399:30"/>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:20399:30"/>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>MAIESTRATES OF CITIES. The dangerous Miſchiefes, <hi>that the</hi> DICING-HOVSES, <hi>and other</hi> lyke Sanctuaries of iniquitie, do breede in the Cittie of LONDON.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ſufficiently</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, that, by the vertue, diligence, and wiſdom, of the right Noble Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, <hi>Alexander: Rome,</hi> (the moſt ouglye, and monſterous Common-wealth of the world, ſo was ſhe deformed, with horrible &amp; beaſtly vices, foſtered by <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> &amp; other wicked Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours,) was brought vnto ſuch perfection, as ſhe might (lawfullye) bee intituled: <hi>The Temple of the Goddes: The Fowntayne of Vertue, and, The Nurce of Learnyng:</hi> ſo free was the Exerciſe of Pietie,<note place="margin">The woundes of a Comon wealth</note> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Temperance, and all other Deuine, Morall, and Heroycall vertues. In curyng of which daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Infirmyties of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth, <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> perfourmed the Offices of a ſkylfull Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Surgion: he did not (ignorantly) apply Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, to the outwarde ſore, vntyll he had ſearched the inward cauſe: He founde, the outwarde woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the Weale-publique, was Pride, Prodigaly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Dicynge, Drunkenneſſe, Lecherie, Vſurie, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueitouſnes &amp;c. The ſuppreſſing of which Paſſions, conſiſted not (alone) in chaſtiſment of Offenders: He (prudently) foreſawe, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Boatman loſt much labor, that with a Diſh, ſtoode all day ladyng out of water, when a quarter of an howres worke, wold
<pb facs="tcp:20399:31"/> mende the breache of his Boate, whiche was the cauſe, althoughe the water were the annoyance: he knew, that euery Ryuer had a Spryng, euery Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, a nooryſhing Humour, and euery vice, a ſpecial ſuccour: Reaſon inſtructed him, that no Thiefe wold be ſo bould, as to rob by the hye waye, if he had no Couert to ſhrowd hym: If there were no Brothell Houſes, Shame wold delay Lechery. But for Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerns and tiplyng Boothes, Drunkardes ſhould be ſober againſt their wils: But for Ordinarie tables, Dicers ſhould (many times) be idle, or better occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied, then in ſwearyng and conſumyng their Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie: Theſe cauſes beynge ſtopped, the vicious (perforce) muſt change their courſe. And therfore, the good Emperour, as the beſt remedie for the mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth, purged <hi>Rome,</hi> of theaſe Sanctuaries of lewd and diſhoneſt perſons, as the perfect meane to cure their vile and naughtie diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. And (certaynly) his Gouernment, Order, and Diſcipline, may be, <hi>A Myrrour for Magiſtrates of all Citties:</hi> who are lyke to finde no lacke of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, to exerciſe his Politique Orders: for, in the heart of the beſt gouerned Citties, Vice hath her Manſion, as a Core in the inward ſubſtance of the ſowndeſt Quince. But, leauyng the Diſcouerie of the Infyrmities of Forreigne Citties, <hi>London,</hi> the Capitol Cittie of <hi>Englande</hi> (and at this day, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon of Chriſtendome,) prowdely beareth many a daungerous Infyrmytie, whiche, the Wiſdome of the Maiſtrates, muſt (ſpeedely) heale, or els, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhortely, the wickedneſſe of her people, wyll abate her proſperytie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:20399:31"/>
                     <head>A Remembrance, of the <hi>Diſordered State of the</hi> Common-wealth, at the Queenes Maieſties commyng to the Crowne.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Queenes moſt</hi> Excellent Maieſtie, (euen our Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) by Gods grace Soueraigne Ladye of this famous Cittie, and of Englande, Fraunce and Irelande (in aduauntage,) ſole Princeſſe of Peace, and ſecond to no annoincted kyng, in the exerciſe of all the Capitol Vertues: let Gods bleſſinges bee my Teſtimonie, (plentifullie) heaped vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her Exellencie, and (for her Holineſſe ſake) vpon her true Subiectes, and many a hungrye Nation, beſides: Her ſacred Maieſtie, (I ſaye) at ſuche time, as ſhe was crowned with the Soueraigntie of theſe Realmes, fownd <hi>ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LANDE,</hi> and (ſpeciallie) <hi>LONDON,</hi> farre out of temper, (beſides Cardinall Superſtition) with carnall and vnchaſte infections of <hi>Rome,</hi> as (alſo) puffed or half poyſoned, with the pryde of <hi>Spayne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For the ſaluynge of which, and all other Infirmy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, of the Common-wealth, her Godly wiſdome, with the Publique aſſent of her Subiectes, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed many Medicinable Lawes, whereby, all the priuye Maladies of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth, might receiue perfect cure, if the Penall Lawes were as ſeuerely puniſhed, as they be (prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly) eſtabliſhed.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20399:32"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Negligence in Maieſtrates cauſeth bouldenes in euill lyuers.</note>But, the (onely) lacke of this Admyniſtration is, the Maieſtrate puniſſheth, but what is preſented, and the Iniured (in many wronges) ſuſtayne their loſſes without complaynt: Thus, lacke of dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, bouldneth the euyll lyuers to offende, with Halters about their neckes.</p>
                     <p>The godly Diuines, in publique Sermons, and others, in printed Bookes, haue (of late) very ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inuayed againſt Stage playes (vnproperly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nvaying againſt ſtage playes.</note> Tragedies, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>medies, and Moralles,) as the Sprynges of many vices, and the ſtumblyng-bloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of Godlyneſſe and Vertue: Truely, the vſe of them vpon the Saboth day, and the abuſe of them at al times, with ſcurilytie and vnchaſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueiance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> miniſtred matter ſufficient for them to blame, and the Maieſtrate to reforme.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Playinge at dice invented by the deuill</note>But, there are in the Bowels of this famous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, farre more daungerous Playes, and little repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended: that wicked Playes of the Dice, firſt inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Deuyll (as <hi>Cornelius Agrippa,</hi> wryteth,) and frequented by vnhappy men: The deteſtable Roote, vpon which, a thouſand villanies growe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ordinarie Tables Nurſes of Iniquitie</note>The Nurſes of theaſe (worſe then Heathnyſh) Helliſh exerciſe, are Places (called) <hi>Ordinary-tables:</hi> Of which, there are, in <hi>London,</hi> more in nomber, to honor the Deuyll, then Churches to ſerue the liuing God: neither are they (improperly) named: for, in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye trueth,<note place="margin">Difference of ordinarie Tables</note> they are the Ordinarie Intertayners of naughtie perſons, and the Sinckes of all abhomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. But ſome wyll holde it conuenient, that I make a Difference of Ordinarie Tables, becauſe, of the ciuill vſage &amp; Orders of ſome of the keepers,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20399:32"/> as in reſpect of the Honourable and worſhipfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre vnto them. In very trueth, in ſome of theſe places, Vice is ſo modeſtly quallyfied, as they may well be called: tollerable euylles. And (although) Socyetie be a pleaſing Affection, I hope, (as occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will fall out) to ſatiſfie the better ſorte of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that, the refraynynge of the beſt of theſe badde Houſes, wyll be more profitable, Honorable &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, then the frequentyng of them.</p>
                     <p>The namyng of the ciuiller ſort, of theſe Houſes, I omyt: becauſe, in reportyng of the viler ſort, and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible vices that they foſter, is farre from my intent: either in name, or figure, to diſcipher any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that keepeth them, or eny Gueſt that haunteth them:<note place="margin">This worke is not made particulerly to blame any perſon, but generally to blaſon abuſe.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtyng before God and man, that my labour ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the roote of this fowle ympoſtume, which vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miteth a nomber of ſeuerall filthy coloured Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: onely, to admoniſh the greener ſort of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who are apteſt to receiue the Infection, and to laye before the Magiſtrate, the Poyſon of theaſe Vlcers: to whoſe wiſdomes, the cure belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth: and in this trauell, I ſuppoſe, I deſerue wel of the worſt liuers, in that I (charitably) admonyſh them, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the euylles, that Time may diſcouer, by their vndoyng: And ſo to my purpoſe,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THere are within the</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vrbes of <hi>London,</hi> diuers worthie Houſes,<note place="margin">Innes of the Court, places of much reuerence.</note> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Innes of the Court and of the Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerie:</hi> Places, where the Lawes of this Realme, are (publiquely) read, ſtudied and learned: Places, of much Honour,
<pb facs="tcp:20399:33"/> and Reputation, aſwell, in reſpect of the Reuerent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Perſonages, whiche gouerne them, as (alſo) for the exerciſe of the Lawes) whiche are the ſtrength and Ornamentes of euery wel gouerned Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth,) euery Gentleman, and (almoſt) Yeman of Abylitie, ſendeth the ripeſt witted of his Children, vnto ſome one of theaſe Houſes, to ſtudy the common Lawes of <hi>Englande.</hi> And (truely) the good Father, in this charge, diſchargeth the loue of a Father towardes his Sonne, and the duetie of a frende, towardes his Countrey: for by ſuche as are learned in the Lawes (if they abuſe not their knowledge) beſides an eſpecial benefit &amp; reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they (priuatly reape) vnto them-ſelues, the Ignorance of their Neighbours where they dwell,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                              <desc>•••••</desc>
                           </gap>ng houſes in a hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the ſtud e of the lawe</note> is (profitably) inſtructed: But, by reaſon of Dicyng-howſes; and other Alectiues too vnthriftineſſe, the good Father, which is at charge, to make his Sonne a Lawier, to do his Countrey ſeruice, throughe the looſeneſſe of the Sonne (many times) ſpendeth his money to the vndooyng of his poſterytie.<note place="margin">One ſcabbed ſheepe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth a hole flocke</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſwarme of Vnthriftes, whiche lyue vpon Shiftes, in, and within the Cittie of <hi>London</hi> (firſt ſeaze vpon theſe Yonglynges: by their lewde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, they drawe them from Studdie, and doo acquaint them with theſe wicked Ordinaries:</p>
                     <p>Wheare, the Brauerie of the Companie, the glee and Reuell that they keepe,<note place="margin">Dye ing houſes, cauſes of pride</note> were able to brynge a ſtayde man vnto their Societie, but are ſure to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt a light yongman, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth (rawly) out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rey. What foloweth? <hi>Pride</hi> (ſtraightwayes) infecteth him with deſire to be as braue as the beſt:</p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:20399:33"/>
                     <p>Well: if he haue liuyng, either in poſſeſſion or poſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, he ſhall finde ſweete Baites to choake him. Moſte of theſe wicked places,<note place="margin">Three dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous gweſtes belonging to ordinarie tables</note> nooriſh three Gueſtes that will ſoundly bowrd this vnexperienced yonge Gentleman, and of his abylitie wyl maintain them ſelues. Theſe be the names of their facultie.</p>
                     <p>The braue Shifter: the Bawde, and the Broaker.</p>
                     <p>¶The braue Companion, who in Apparayle,<note place="margin">Deſcription of braue ſhyfters</note> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce, and bouldnes, wyll cheacke-mate with men of right good worſhyp, and lyuing, when he (perhaps) in a Greene Thycket getteth a Maſked face, a Pyſtoll, and a Whypcorde, and hath Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce in the Ile of <hi>Snatch:</hi> Aduentureth to Cape <hi>Gripe:</hi> I know not by what conning ſhiftes. But if I did, I thinke it neceſſary to conceale them, leaſt the inſtruction wold prooue more hurtful to the euill inclined, then the Admonition, profitable, to the wel diſpoſed: But this, I am aſſured, and many a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans vndoyng, witneſſeth as muche: that theſe expert Shifters, by falce Dice, ſlipperie caſtynge, or ſome other nice Sleight: althoughe all the Daye, they dallye with younge Nouices.<note place="margin">Braue ſhiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters lyue vp on the coſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of play</note> as a Catte doeth with a Mouſe: yet, before Bedde tyme, they wyll make their Purſes as emptie of Money, as the Catte the Mouſes headde of Braynes.</p>
                     <p>If a man had none other Flie ſuckynge of hym, he ſhould finde, a fewe of Ordinarie Dinners would ſuppe a greate deale of Subſtaunce. But, as a ſlayne Carckaſe, in an open Fielde, is a Pray
<pb facs="tcp:20399:34"/> pray, for many kyndes of vermyn. Euen ſo, a plaine minded man vſing theſe deceitful houſes, is an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red praye for al ſortes of ſhyfters.</p>
                     <p>The man that is inticed to be a Dicer, of his owne accorde wil be a Horemaſter: But (ſay you) if he haue not acquaintance, the baniſhment of the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes wyl kepe hym chaſt. But ſay as the Prouerbe is. <hi>Monie will hyre a guide to go to the Deuile:</hi> And <hi>(certes)</hi> as dailie gheaſts at ordinarie Tabls, a man ſhal fynde neate Bawdes,<note place="margin">Brokers of Bawdry. haunters of Dycing hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </note> that onely lyue vppon the brocage of loue, fellowes that wyl procure ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintaunce for a dumbe man. Theſe be no baſhful <hi>Beſogniers,</hi> but ſuch as glory in their facultie. Their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon talke ſhalbe Ribaldry, and matter of their profeſſion. To conclude, he that hath aduantage, ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bloweth a meeting of faire women into my yong maiſters eares: His company needeth not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. Incontinent deſire maketh him wood of their ſocietie. Gods blood, lets goe, ſtraight he cryeth, and with more haſte, then good ſpeede, they goe to ſome blind brothel-houſe wher (peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture) for a Pottle or two of wyne, the imbracement of a paynted Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, and the French Pockes for a reckoning, the <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> payeth fortie ſhillings,<note place="margin">Coſſonage of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>awdes.</note> and yet my braue <hi>Beſog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier</hi> hath a more coſtly reckoning to geue hym. He wyl accompanie him familierly vp and downe the Citie, and in the ende wyll come vnto a Mercers or a Gold-ſmythes ſhop, with whome he had before ſet his matche, he wyl cheapen, Veluet, Satten, Iuels, or what hym lyketh, and tender his owne &amp; companions credit for payment: He wyll with ſo boulde a countenaunce aſke this frendſhyp of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20399:34"/> Gentleman, as the other ſhalbe to ſeeke of excuſe to denie him: Well, although the peniworthes of the one, be not verye good, the payment of the other, is ſure to be currant: thus, by vnſatiable Ryot, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Dicyng Houſes are the Fowntaynes, the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt of our yong Gentlemen, are ſoone learned to ſynge.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>¶ <hi>Diues eram dudum, ſed tria, mé fecerunt nudum,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Alia, vina, venus, tribus his, ſum factus egenus.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I wealthie was of late, though naked now you ſée:</l>
                        <l>Thrée things haue chaunged mine eſtate. Dice, Wine, and Lecherie.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>¶But (without doubt) the infection of theaſe Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Houſes, is ſo pleaſant, that a man which hath loſt all his money, by the exerciſe of them, euen, in the place of his vndoyng, he wyll (moneyleſſe) be an idle looker on, of other mens vnthriftineſſe.</p>
                     <p>Then ſeazeth the third of theaſe Gheaſtes vpon this needie Gentleman, which is: <hi>The Broaker:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Brokers for mony and their Coſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage.</note> who is (either) an olde Ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ckrupt Citizin: or ſom ſmoothe condicioned vnthriftie Gentleman, farre in debte: ſome one of theſe wyll help him to credit, with ſome of their Creditors, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſingle proteſtation of meere courteſie: But (by your fauour) vppon this double vzance: the Citizyn Broaker, after deduction for his owne paynes, conſideration for the time giuen, and loſſe in ſellyng of the wares conſidered: wyll bryng him. L V. pounds, currant money, for a. C-pownds good debt: The Gentleman Broaker, will deale more <hi>Caualiero</hi>-like: he will be bownde with hym for a.C, pownds, ſhaarynge the Money betweene them, not without ſolempne proteſtation, faithfully
<pb facs="tcp:20399:35"/> to diſcharge his owne fiftie powndes, and (if neede be) the whole hundred powndes: Aſſuraunce (truſt mee) as good as a Statute Staple, and a meaſure of his foote, as ſure as eyther. But, let all this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe go: here is want ſupplied, whiche breaketh Braſen walles: and Money receyued, whiche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayeth Kynges. blindeth Iudges, and iudgeth Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: and for the ſame, but Incke, Waxe and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chement, deliuered: Mary (ſir) a merye exchange: a mery Exchange (in deed) if a man ſhuld (alwayes) be ſo buſied in receiuyng, as there might be no lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure fownde for repayment:<note place="margin">A good leſſon for younge Gentlemen.</note> But (vnhappy young Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) what ſo thou bee that art thus matched: thoughe thy coueitous loue of Money is (lightly) ſuche, as thou haddeſt rather become Debter for fortie powndes, then to ſpare fortie ſhyllynges out of thy own Purſe: yet learn this Leſſon (as a ſound Counſel:) that thou weart better giue one of theſe Franions, ten pownds, then to be bound for fiftene: for, what ſo remaineth, thou ſaueſt, when all that thou ventureſt, thou looſeſt: and be thou ſure, though thou wilt finde no leaſure to ſatiſfie thy couenaunt, thy Creditor wyll worke thee an Arreſt, that ſhall giue thee little eaſe, and leſſe Lybertie, vntyll he be fully contented &amp; paid.<note place="margin">Prodigalitie a paſſion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable.</note> But al in vain Medicine is applied to vncurable Maladies: as ſmallie auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth good Counſell giuen vnto the Prodigall.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ib. de liberalit</note>
                        <hi>Prodigalytie</hi> &amp; <hi>Coueitouſneſſe,</hi> are two extreame Paſſions, and as violent are their cures: <hi>Begerie,</hi> is the ende of <hi>Prodigalytie,</hi> &amp; <hi>Death,</hi> of <hi>Coueitouſneſſe:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Yet, as <hi>Iouius Pontanus</hi> ſaith, the Coueitous man is the worſt of both: for he doth no man (not ſo much as himſelf) good w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his goods: when the Prodigal, by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20399:35"/> the vndoing of himſelf, inricheth many. Thus, what may be beſt ſaid of <hi>Prodigalyte,</hi> concludeth an vndo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of him-ſelf &amp; poſterytie. The famous Lawier <hi>Vlpianus</hi> ſaith: the prodigal man, neither obſerueth time, nor maketh end of riot, vntil riot hath, both co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed him &amp; his Patrimony. The ſage <hi>Solo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> made a law, to defame prodigal men. The <hi>Areopagites,</hi> and criminal Iudges of <hi>Athens,</hi> puniſhed prodigall me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as idle, vagrant &amp; vnprofitable me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The .x. Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors of <hi>Rome,</hi> made a law, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prodigal me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould neither haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouerme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nor diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their own goods: but vnto him ſhuld be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a <hi>Curator,</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poinctme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iudge. By the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of <hi>Q. Pompeius,</hi> Pretor, <hi>Q, Fabius,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Son of <hi>Q. Fabius,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Vale. Max. li 3. Cha. 5.</note> the great (ſurnamed) <hi>Allobrogique</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riotous diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his Patrimonie, was indited by this law, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouernment of a Tutor. Were this law executed in <hi>England,</hi> we ſhuld haue more War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, of .xxxv. then .xv. yeares of Age. The <hi>Gretians,</hi> had a law, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whoſoeuer had vnthriftily co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed his patrimony, ſhuld not be buried in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſepulchre of his Aunceſtors, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was held vnworthie the Honor of his Aunceſtors, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diſhonoreth himſelfe, &amp; robbeth his poſterytie. The ancient, graue &amp; politique Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-wealth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thus ſeuerely chaſtned <hi>Prodigalytie:</hi> though prodigal men had no care of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-ſelues, they tendered the poſterytie of their poſterytie: they (like vnto careful Phiſitions, that prouide preſeruatiues becauſe the infection of the Plague is daungerous) ſought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Prodigalytie might not be noo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhed: fore-ſeeyng that prodigall men, neyther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced good Counſayle, nor feared Diſciplyne.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20399:36"/>
                     <p>And (ſurely) it is a worke of greater Iuſtice, merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie, to find a way to preſerue men from offending then (ſeuerely) to puniſh euery offence.</p>
                     <p>Suppreſſe theſe vnthriftie Houſes, and you ſhall keepe many a mans Landes from ſellyng, many a mans neck from the Halter, &amp; the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth, (perhaps) from a more daungerous miſchiefe.</p>
                     <p>I haue (but yet) begun, to anatomize the Head, of this villanous Sanctuarie of Iniquitie, a heape of euilles followe. The deceipt of Dice, the charge of Lecherie, Coſonage and Brocage, is all that I haue yet layde vpon our vnhappy Gentlman:</p>
                     <p>Theſe (onely) pray vpon Gould, Siluer, and ſuche light carraidge. Theſe be but ſuckyng Flies, the bityng Scorpions come after. A Byrde that hath but one feather limed, by ſtriuing, fetreth her whole body: Euen ſo, the vnfortunate Gentleman, thruſt behinde the hande, by the hazard of Dice, through a vaine hope, to redeeme himſelfe, followeth his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, to the ſpendynge of the laſt payment of his Lande, And to helpe him forwarde, ſome one Spie or Pettifogger of the Lawe (the reuerence done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Law and good Lawiers reuerenced,<note place="margin">A Petifogger a moſt daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note>) I may iuſtly ſaye, the Scum of all villanie, is (euer-more) ſneakyng in theſe Ordinarie Houſes: This nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Companion, keepeth an Alphabet, of all the rich Gentlemens names, that frequenteth the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries:<note place="margin">Exercyſe of ordinarie Table pety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foggers.</note> his eyes are ſettled vpon their diſpoſitions, and his exerciſe is, dayly, to ſearch the Rolles, and the Office of the Statutes, to learn what Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zances, Morguages and Statutes do charge their Landes: This is the moſt pernitious Broaker, the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20399:36"/> other helped the needie gentleman to money at fiftie in the hundred loſſe, but he helpeth him to ſell free land at fiue yeres purchaſe.</p>
                     <p>I muſt here digreſſe from the prodigalitie of the gentleman, vnto the couetouſneſſe and vſurie, I can not properly ſay of the Citizen, although he dwelleth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citie: for the true Citizen (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>London</hi> hath plentie) liueth vpon his trade, be he an aduenturer abroade, or a mecanicall crafts man at home.<note place="margin">Couetous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens hunt ordinarie ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to vndoe Gentlemen.</note> But theſe ſhames of good Citizens tradeth but to a dycing houſe, or at the furtheſt trauaileth to a bowling alley, and with eaſe &amp; ſafetie getteth wealth as faſt as the other doe with great hazard and trauell. They come not to play the vnthrifts, but to pray vpon vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts: and yet for companie, and to auoide ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition, they wil ſometime play the good fellowes. All the reſt are but inſtruments for theſe daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous catchers. Theſe neede not too greedily ſeeke for purchaſes, the neceſſitie of the gentlemen maketh them faire offers: and their ſpies, the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifogger and others giueth them knowledge where there is ſound dealing. Among them there is ſuch deceit coloured with ſuch cleanly ſhifts, as many gentlemen are for a trifle ſhifted out of their liuings without hope of remedie.<note place="margin">The extreme dealing of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens haue ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a deadly enuie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and merchaunts.</note> The extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of theſe mens dealings hath beene and is ſo cruell, as there is a natural malice generally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the hearts of the gentlemen of <hi>England</hi> towards the citizens of <hi>London,</hi> inſomuch as if they odiouſly name a man, they foorthwith call him <hi>A trimme merchaunt.</hi> In like deſpight the
<pb facs="tcp:20399:37"/> Citizen calleth euery raſcall <hi>A ioly Gentleman.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And truely this mortall enuie betweene theſe two woorthie eſtates, was firſt engendred of the cruell vſage of couetous merchaunts, in hard bargaines gotten of Gentlemen, and nouriſhed with malitious words and reuenges taken of both parties.<note place="margin">Tim. 1. cap. 6. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> of couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> 
                        <hi>S. Paul</hi> by good warrant ſaith, <hi>That couetouſneſſe is the roote of all miſchiefe. S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſaith, that the couetous man is ſubiect to all euils, for that all euils come of couetouſneſſe. He moreouer ſaith, that wilde beaſts haue mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for being hungrie they purſue their praies, and being full are ſatiſfied: but the couetous man is neuer ſatiſfied. He neither feareth God, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenceth man, pardoneth not his father, nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth his mother, maketh merchandize of his children, regardeth not his brother, nor yet keepeth faith w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his friend, beareth falſe witneſſe, offendeth the widow, &amp; deſtroyeth the Infant. O how great is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> follie of our vnderſtanding, to loſe life, to ſeeke death, &amp; to baniſh ourſelues from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen:<note place="margin">Foure wheeles of the chariot of couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The two horſes. The waggo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. The two whippes.</note> 
                        <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the accurſed chariot of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, is drawen with foure diſloyall wheeles of vices, <hi>vz. Puſalanimite, Crueltie miſpriſing of God, and forgetfulneſſe of certaine death.</hi> The two horſes are named <hi>Theft,</hi> &amp; <hi>Hardneſſe.</hi> The waggo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is <hi>Earneſt deſire to haue,</hi> who vſeth two ſharpe whippes: the one called <hi>Diſordered appetite to get,</hi> the other, <hi>Feare to looſe.</hi> The opinion of <hi>Apuleius</hi> in his firſt booke of Magicke is woorthy to be read, who writeth thus. The Philoſopher <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> had not ſo much riches as <hi>Lelius,</hi> nor <hi>Lelius</hi> ſomuch as <hi>Scipio,</hi> nor <hi>Scipio</hi> ſo much as the rich
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20399:37"/> 
                        <hi>Craſſus,</hi> nor <hi>Craſſus</hi> ſo much riches as he deſired. The Emperour <hi>Pertinax</hi> was ſo couetous,<note place="margin">Pertinax Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</note> as he would inuite his friends vnto two ſmall ſlyces of meate and a diſh of apples, and when he would ſeeme moſt ſumptuous and magnificent, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the two genitories of a cocke. <hi>Iouian Pontanus</hi> ſaith, that Pope <hi>Martin</hi> was ſo couetous,<note place="margin">Pope Martin.</note> as he would ſteale euerie night the burning tapers in <hi>S. Peters</hi> Church. The ſame <hi>Pontanus</hi> ſaith, that a Cardinal named <hi>Angel,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Cardinall An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell.</note> euerie night would ſteale away from his own horſes bottels of hay, and ſel them to other oſtlers, vntill his horſekeeper one night (taking of him tardy) ſwinged him cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly.<note place="margin">Couetouſnes a dangerous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie to the common wealth.</note> To conclude the euils of couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, with the daungers it bringeth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth vnto. Men that haue licentiouſly ſpent their ſubſtance, and finde no liberalitie to ſupplie their wants, wiſh ſtraight wayes an alteration of the eſtate, and what in them lieth practiſeth the ſam. They fawne vpon ambitious men which are in authority, &amp; betweene whom of the noble men is enuie, diſdaine, or priuat diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, they help forward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faction, they ſeeke mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſedition, which being not wiſely ſuppreſſed, ciuil commotions, battell, &amp; deſtruction of people oftentimes followeth. Reade y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hiſtories of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; you ſhal find, that couetouſneſſe and vſurie haue begun many commotions, and could not be ended vntil the inſtruments &amp; bonds of debt were can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled. We need not ſearch ſo farre, <hi>England</hi> &amp; al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nations cary a large teſtimony in their own Chronicles of this fowle matter, and therefore
<pb facs="tcp:20399:38"/> 
                        <hi>Thucidides</hi> ſaith not vnproperly, That couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is the nurſe of murther, theft, periurie, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon &amp; all abhominations: not for that couetous men practiſe theſe villanies, but for that by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme neceſſitie they driue men to theſe wicked ſhifts.</p>
                     <p>I heard a Frenche Gentleman reſolue a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme very pleaſauntly and pithily.<note place="margin">A probleme pithily aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by a Frenche Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilman.</note> An Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man demaunded the cauſe, That the young gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilmen of <hi>Fraunce</hi> flouriſhed more than they of <hi>England,</hi> conſidering that the one were conſumed with daily warre, when the other had continuall peace to ſtrengthen them. O quoth the Frenche Gentleman, The quietneſſe of your peace inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth not the deceit of your Citizens, who with the feeding of your pride, deuoureth your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings: when with vs the troubles of warre ſo feare them, as to ſaue the ſworde from their throtes, they giue vs the golde in their cheſts. Fowle fall couetouſneſſe and vſurie which prooueth his ſaying true, and more grace or fewe daies happen vnto couetous wretches, who with the vndooing of many in the ende vndoe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Socrates common wealth poore.</note>
                        <hi>Socrates</hi> found that aboundance of wealth was the ouerthrowe of many common wealthes, and therefore in his owne common wealth, he would haue the common people poore, and the reſt not to haue too much: ſaying that wealth bred pride, and pride all miſchiefes, when pouertie brought foorth Science, and all good Arts, and Science all maner of earthly happineſſe. Thus one miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20399:38"/> draweth on an other, and dyeing houſes are the fountaines.</p>
                     <p>Theſe wicked houſes firſt nuſleth our young gentlemen in pride, and acquainteth them with ſundrie ſhifting companions, whereof one ſort couſeneth him at dice and cardes, an other ſort conſume him with lecherie, an other ſort by bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadge bringeth him in debt, and out of credit, then awayteth couetouſneſſe and vſurie to ſeaſe vpon his liuing, and the vnciuill Sergeant vpon his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie. To ruine is thus brought the gentleman, a great eſtate and ſtrength of this Realme, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally by the frequenting of dicing houſes.</p>
                     <p>Let vs ſearche deeper into this vlcer, there is more fowle matter behinde, we haue but yet ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the better ſort of dicing houſes, which are chiefelie for intertainement of Courtiers and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gentlemen, which by reaſon of their atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce and buſineſſe keepe no certaine houſes. If ordinarie tables be tollerated for their neceſſitie, what warrant haue the ordinarie table-keepers within the heart of <hi>London,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ordinaries for Citizens and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience.</note> (which are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called dicing houſes) for Citizens? In euerie Citie, Citizens haue houſes of their owne, haue wife, children and families to care for: and ſure the inconuenience cannot but be great, when a man leaueth his owne houſe, and the companie of his wife and familie, and dineth at a dicing houſe. In many well gouerned common wealths, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens by eſpeciall Lawes were forbidden to eate and drinke out of their owne houſes, vnleſſe one neighbour inuited an other: but ſufferance hath
<pb facs="tcp:20399:39"/> brought this miſchiefe to ſuch a cuſtome, that if there were many more Citizens ordinaries, they ſhould not need to fawn vpon the inferior ſort for want of companie of ſubſtantiall Citizens. But before we enter further into this miſchiefe,<note place="margin">Keeper of theſe houſes ſhame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the keepers of theſe places is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, for the moſt part the maſters of theſe hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in times paſt haue beene bankrouts, &amp; what may be expected of men of their diſpoſitions? ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a continuance of their facultie, to liue vpon the goods of other men. Hither repaire al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloſe ſhif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, here many notorious couſinages are ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſters of theſe houſes want no gueſts, for where carrion is, crowes will be plentie, and where money is ſturring, cheters will not be idle. You<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g citizens for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part depend vpon their credit, &amp; therfore are loath that there ſhould be an open teſtimony of their vnthriftines. Al the better for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biting cheter. Cloſe in a chamber a cogging knaue getteth more money in an houre, than ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny an honeſt man ſpendeth in a yere. And this one thing is much to be lamented, the vnthrifty citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſume other mens goods, who perhaps la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured painfully to get the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (when gentlemen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they vndoe their poſterite) ſpend but their own goods &amp; lands. The eares of the magiſtrate are daily ful of the breaking of yong merchants, &amp; here I lay before their eies the cauſes therof, euen theſe wicked ordinaries. They be places vnto which magiſtrates come not, &amp; therefore the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vnknowen vnto them. But I think it a work of much honeſty to reueale them, and in the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate a work of more iuſtice to reforme them, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20399:39"/> vndoubtedly although this be true that I write, &amp; the euils far more than I diſcouer, yet in diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering of the faults &amp; faultie men, I find my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſo free from their ſhiftes, as in writing my name to this booke, I preſume, that no man (as faultie in that part of reprehenſion) will ſay,
<q>Turpe eſt doctori, cum culpa redarguit ipſum.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>But as one that meaneth not to complaine his loſſes, to ioyn my owne example with admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly determine to croſſe the ſtreets where theſe vile houſes are planted, to bleſſe me from the inticements of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which in very deed are many, &amp; the more dangerous in that they pleaſe with a vain hope of gain.<note place="margin">A dicers opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the fi ſt making of dice &amp; cards.</note> Inſomuch on a time I heard a diſtemperate dicer ſolemly ſweare, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he faithfully beleeued, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dice were firſt made of the bones of a witch, &amp; cards of her ſkin, in which there hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſithence remained an inchantment, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer once taketh delight in either, he ſhall neuer haue power vtterly to leaue them, for quoth he, I a hundred times vowed to leaue both, yet haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace to forſake either. But for al his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if <hi>Socrates</hi> alterd his natural inclination of inſolencie by philoſophie: if the wiſe <hi>Vliſſes</hi> could eate of the herb called <hi>Lotos,</hi> &amp; yet by the pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe therof would not be inchanted to remaine in that countrie, when his companions &amp; ſeruants (forgetting their natural land) coueted to remain ſtil in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> region where that herb grewe, &amp; but only by violence they could not be brought back again to their ſhips: if heathen men only by philoſophie could maſter their diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, chriſtians by praier &amp; philoſophy may ouercome an inticing miſchiefe.
<pb facs="tcp:20399:40"/> But vnto this poſſibilitie of reformation, wiſe men are to giue light credence. Olde Iudge <hi>Chomley</hi> euermore aunſwered naughtie liuers that ſued for mercie, deſiring him to regard the frailtie of young men, by the bolde and vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful actions of his owne youth, and by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his grace, good fortune, and preſent autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, to conceiue hope of their amendement: O my friendes,<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>udge Chom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ys aunſwere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o theeues that ſued for mercie.</note> quoth the Iudge, I tel you plainly, that of twentie that in thoſe dayes were my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, I onely eſcaped hanging: and it is very like, that ſome one of your fellowſhip is by Gods goodneſſe reſerued to be an honeſt man, but you are found offenders by the Lawe, and truely iuſtice (whoſe ſentence I am ſworne to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce) commaundeth me to commend your ſoules to Almightie God, and your bodies to the Gallowſe. This notable Iudge in his aunſwere was not <hi>ſhort and ſweete,</hi> but <hi>round and ſeuere.</hi> Great is the pitie that of twentie offenders there ſhould but one become a good man. Howe high a worke were it then of charitie and mercie to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue men from notable offences? Certainly farre greater, than to pardon offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders. For by the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the firſt, vice ſhall be driuen to her ſhifts, when the mildeneſſe of the ſeconde many times breedeth preſumption. If the good magiſtrates of this Citie, vſed the diligence of the fore reported Cenſors of <hi>Rome,</hi> in ſhort ſpace the caſe would be altered, and in time cuſtome would make men honeſt, which without diſcipline can haue no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. There is an olde prouerbe, <hi>The eye of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20399:40"/> the maſter, doth as much worke as the handes of the ſeruant.</hi> If the magiſtrats ſurueide but theſe vile houſes by honeſt conſeruators, you ſhould finde the painefull trauels of capital Magiſtrats much eaſed, many mens liues ſhalbe ſaued, Gentleman ſhall haue more lande, and Citizens greater ſtore of money: which mettall is the greateſt ſtrength of a Citie, for where mony is not ſcarce,<note place="margin">Citizens for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe lande.</note> traficke is plentie, which chiefly ſupporteth al Cities. And therfore in many wel gouerned co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthes, Citizens (to the ende they ſhould onely imploie their money in traficke) were forbidden to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe lande, other than a garden for recreation. But to my purpoſe, theſe deuelliſh houſes are cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that merchants haue ſo much lande, and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen ſo litle vertue.</p>
                     <p>It is alreadie ſhowen, to what extremitie the better ſort of theſe houſes bring a great number of our flouriſhing Gentlemen. To what miſerie the ſeconde ſort (called ordinaries for Citizens) bring a great number of young merchauntes. Nowe remayneth the diſcouerie of the thirde ſort of theſe hauntes, which are placed in Allies,<note place="margin">Ordinaries for maſterles me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhifters, &amp;c.</note> gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and other obſcure corners out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon walks of the Magiſtrate. The dayly gueſts of theſe priuie houſes, are maiſterles men, needy ſhifters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> theeues, cutpurſes, vnthriftie ſeruants, both ſeruing men, and prentiſes. Heere a man may picke out mates for all purpoſes, ſaue ſuch as are good. Heere a man may finde out <hi>Brauoes</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Naples,</hi> who for a pottle of wine, will make no more conſcience to kill a man, than a Butcher a beaſt, heare cloſely lie good fellowes,
<pb facs="tcp:20399:41"/> that with a good Northren Gelding, will gaine more by a halter, than an honeſt yeoman will with a teame of good horſes. Heare are they, that will not let to deceaue their father, to robbe their brother, and fire their neighbours houſe for an aduauntage. Theſe frannions will not ſticke to ſpende frankely, although they haue neither landes nor goods by the dead, nor honeſtie by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. But how will this hould out? fire will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume wood without maintenance, and ryot a weake purſe without ſupply. The Gentlemen (for the moſt haue landes to make money, and young marchants waies to get credite, but the moſt of theſe idle perſons haue neither landes nor credite, nor will liue by an honeſt occupation: forſooth they haue yet handes to filch, heades to deceiue, and friendes to receiue: and by theſe helpes, ſhift meetely badly well. The other vpon currant aſſurance, perhaps get money, for twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie markes or twenty poundes in the hundred. But theſe that worſt may hould the candle they vpon their owne, or maiſters apparell, braſſe, pewter, ſheetes, ſhirts, &amp;c. finde Brokers, or frip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perers, that for a ſhilling in the pounde, for euery moneth, will bouldly, for halfe the vallue take theſe paunes. Certainely it ſeemeth that <hi>London</hi> is ſore charged with theſe makeſhiftes, for that almoſt in euery ſtreate and lane there dwelleth two or three of theſe pettie brokers, or <hi>cheriſh-theeues.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> And I pray to God, that in Cheape ſide, and other principall ſtreates, although gould, ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, ſilkes and other coſtly merchandiſe be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſhops, that in many mens cofers there
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20399:41"/> lie not Cardinall <hi>Campeius</hi> ſumpter riches.<note place="margin">Learne this Cardinals name.</note> Fiftie or ſixtie in the hundred is ſweete gaine, and a double par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne taketh away all feare of the ſtatute. A Iuiſh vſurie, high time to bee rooted out of a Chriſtian gouernement. By ouer long ſufferaunce howe much <hi>London</hi> hath blemiſhed her auncient vertues, and indaungered her peace and proſperitie, is not to be recounted. In the time of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, the good citizens of <hi>London</hi> in one night ſlew fiue hundred Iewes for that a Iewe tooke of a Chriſtian a pennie in the ſhilling vſurie: and euer after got them bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the Citie: if the like Iuſtice were done vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Iuiſh Chriſtians, <hi>London</hi> would haue manie houſes emptie, and her Churches and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeardes would he too ſcant to receiue dead car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rions. Truely theſe <hi>Atheiſts</hi> deſerue worſe than Iewes, for they more ſharply execute the trade of Iewes. The Iewes ſpoile not one another, but Chriſtians, whom they eſteeme as dogges, when theſe counterfets make no difference of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. The good Maieſtrates muſt ouerlooke this euill, or elſe the euill will ouerrule their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie. It is a great miracle (but that God is mercifull) that this Citie is not alwaies gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly afflicted with the plague, when ſacred is the authoritie that ſayth, <hi>The plague ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the houſe of the ſwearer.</hi> I imagaine that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers cure one poyſon with an other, who gape ſo wide to blaſpheme God, as they ſwallowe the Deuil into their bowels, vpon whom no plague but hell fire will faſten. How needefull a thing is it to looke vnto theſe places where this outrage
<pb facs="tcp:20399:42"/> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>one vnto God. Thirde you they may not he made inſtruments to nouriſh traiterous prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes? The conſpiracie of <hi>Madder</hi> and <hi>Barloe,</hi> was hatched in a tabling houſe, in the white fryers. Where is the currant of newes but in tabling houſes, forraine explorers and faulſe ſubiectes, there heare much matter intreated at counſell bordes. Where is a deſperate <hi>Athieſt</hi> like vnto harebraine <hi>Someruile</hi> ſo ready to be found, as in a tabeling houſe? Obſtinate Papiſts that dare not liue in the countrey for feare of the ſtatute, monethly ſhift their lodgings, and without ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition heere dayly receiue their dyet. Launce an olde feaſtred ſore, and you are like to finde corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion more than of one humour. But admit they proue no baites for ſuch purpoſes: they are the ſinkes of the fore reported miſchiefes. The vndo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many, and the honeſt gaine of no man. The Gentleman excuſeth his repaire to them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he keepeth no certaine houſe, and likewiſe alleadgeth conuerſation of equals: but as he fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no thrift in the firſt, ſo he is often deceiued in the ſeconde. A tabling houſe is like vnto a ſtrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, who is readie to receiue euery mans money. And many times men of great worſhippe, are hearded, and braued, with inferiours to ſome of their ſeruantes. The Gentleman of <hi>Naples</hi> is highly to be commended, for this honorable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, how meane ſo euer his liuing be, yet he will furniſh his owne table:<note place="margin">The honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſpoſition of the Napo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ion gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> ſo he both auoydeth the controulement of ſuperiours, and the cheeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of inferiours. Would our Engliſh gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men did the like, they would like very well of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20399:42"/> change. By this frugallitie, the <hi>Napolitane</hi> liueth <hi>Cauelie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> like with a 100. trownes a yeare, and our ryot maketh no ſhowe of ſo much a moneth. But you will ſay they ſtarue themſelues: but did euer any ſee a man to die of hunger, where meate was to be ſold, if he had gaie clothes to his backe, it ſeemeth he contenteth nature, which is plentie ynough, we for our glutonie are euerie where cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Engliſh bellies. Very few of our gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> die old men by inordinate feading, our memorie, wit, and minde, which is immortall, is daylie dulled, weakened and almoſt ſlaine by ſurfets. Let vs excuſe the matter as we pleaſe, wee receiue no better remedie by our excuſe, than <hi>Mahomet</hi> had for the fawling ſickneſſe, by coloring his diſeaſe, in giuing out that his paſſion proceeded of the brightneſſe of an Angell, which in thoſe fittes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed heauenly matters vnto him. But if men will deceiue them ſelues by deluding others, they ſhall finde had I wiſt a bitter pill to digeſt. I neede ſhewe no other examples than the daylie falles of young Gentlemen that truſt to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of theſe intiſing dicing houſes, where ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is ſhut in the cole ſeller, and vice and all co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning villanies, ſet in the chiefe places of the hall. And therefore happie is he, that is either aduiſed by good counſell, or warned by other mens harmes.</p>
                     <p>A care to continue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proſperitie of this famous Citie, will no doubt cauſe her Capitall magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſhortly to looke into the behauiours of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otous Citizens, their vnthriftineſſe conſumeth more than their owne goods, and vndoeth many,
<pb facs="tcp:20399:43"/> that trauaile painefully for their liuing. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of monethly iuſtice, ſufficeth to diſmay the third ſort of vnthriftie liuers. There are more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted from Newgate and the Marſhalſies, than in three of the greateſt Cities of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and yet I truely ſay, that more offenders are fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably quitted, and pardoned in <hi>London</hi> in one moneth,<note place="margin">The excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ercie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Queenes Maieſtie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> than in <hi>Paris</hi> in a whole yere, ſo exceeding great is the mercie of our moſt good Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> the remembraunce whereof may not paſſe without zealous thankes vnto God for her thriſe excellent Maieſtie, leaſt ſtraungers condemne her naturall ſubiects of ingratitude, who to eternize this pretious vertue of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, rooted in the magnanimous heart of her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, in commemoration thereof, haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten many learned bookes. Others haue raiſed diſputationn, whether it be a vertue more holy, in her Maieſtie, or daungerous for her true ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects: for feare leaſt her clemencie extend vnto perſons of the diſpoſition of the froſen ſnake, which the pitifull huſbandman cheriſhed by the fire, vntill ſhe offered to ſting his children: and truely whether preſumption or neceſſitie were the cauſe, I leaue to iudge: but I craue Gods wrath as iuſtice, if I ſpeake not the trueth: <hi>In Rome, euen in that Rome, where the Pope and her woorſt enemie raigneth, among Engliſh fugitiues, not woorthie of the benefite of her good ſubiects, plentie, peace and proſperitie. There was (which with mine owne eares I heard) that wiſhed impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment in the Fleete at the Queenes mercie, rather than libertie in Rome.</hi> It is apparant that her
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20399:43"/> Highneſſe mildenes exceedeth, and it ſeemeth that the Popes bountie is not verie plentiful, ſaue vnto ſuch, as rather carrie ſedition than zeale in their counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. When ſuch as cannot be contented to be good ſubiects, affie more in her clemencie (if ſhame held the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not backe) than in the Popes holineſſe, for all his gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſhowes. In my booke entituled, <hi>The bleſſings of Peace,</hi> this digreſſion ſhall be liuely ſet foorth. In the meane ſpace &amp; many happy yeres after, I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech Almightie God to forget our vnworthineſſe, by remembrance of her worthineſſe, that ſhe may in al fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie ſtill raigne among vs as the image of his glorie, and the comfort of all true Chriſtians. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Againe to my purpoſe: Though there cannot be too much good ſpoken of her Maieſties gratious &amp; ſweet mercie, yet ſeueritie may no wayes be termed cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſo that no more than Lawe be miniſtred to nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble malefactors. <hi>London</hi> is ſo plentifull of notorious couſeners, cheters, and diſhoneſt liuers, and withall ſo blemiſhed with heynous couſenages and deceites, as a young man, vnleſſe he haue an olde mans expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, can hardly auoide their ſnares.</p>
                     <p>Many newe kinde of ſhiftes, which none but the Deuill could inuent, and verie <hi>Atheiſtes</hi> execute, by the wiſedome of graue Maieſtrates haue beene ſyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted foorth: wherein reuerent perſonages were in danger of diſhonour, and innocentes in hazarde of death. It is a matter of freſh memorie. The pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke miſchiefe that of late yeares was hatched in theſe wicked houſes, and growento the great loſſe, hinderance, and halfe vndoing of more than two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Gentlemen, honeſt citizens and yeomen, yet God which is iuſt, hath rewarded many of the decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb facs="tcp:20399:44"/> according to their euill deſeruings.</p>
                     <p>No man was euer aſſaulted with a more daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſtrategeme of coſonage than my ſelfe, with which my life &amp; liuing was hardly beſet. No man hath more cauſe to thanke God for a free deliuery than my ſelfe, nor anie man euer ſawe, more ſuddaine veligeance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted vpon his aduerſaries, than I my ſelfe of mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as liuely appeareth in the ende of my booke intituled <hi>The rocke of regarde,</hi> imprinted many yeares paſt.</p>
                     <p>And although to cure the extremitie I then fared as a man ſore ſcalded with fire, which in hope of eaſe leapeth into colde water, which preſently ſtripeth off his ſkin. So I that had experience of ſtrangers huge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eceite, thought that the pleaſing perſwaſion of neare friendes, would turne to a comfortable remedie, but I finde the olde Larkes ſong true: <hi>There is no truſt in faire words, nor aſſurance in natures obligations.</hi> But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter three yeares &amp; more of coſtly ſute my greeuous op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion (God be therfore prayſed) hath pearſed the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining eares, of the right Honorable, and Gracious Iudge, the L. Chauncelor of Englande: by whoſe wiſedom &amp; graue iudgement, I conſtantly beleeue, for he releued &amp; releaſed of the toile of Law: vpon whoſe commaundement, with all humilitie, reuerence and dutie I attend, beſeeching Almighty God to preſerue the bleſſed eſtate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Queenes moſt excellent maieſtie here vpon earth, the lieuetenant of his diuine graces: the right honorable Lordes of the priuie Counſell, the true images of wiſedome: and all other Capitall and good Magiſtrates, the ſtrong pillers of this happie gouernement. And to the friendly readers of this booke, I wiſh the benefit of my trauels, and to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenders amendment of life.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20399:44"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
